<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The addicions of Salem and Byzance</title>
            <author>Saint German, Christopher, 1460?-1540.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1534</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104697</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840430</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840430</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4934</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11323)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4934)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 145:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The addicions of Salem and Byzance</title>
                  <author>Saint German, Christopher, 1460?-1540.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72, [3] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In aedibus Thomae Bertheleti regii impressoris,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.XXXIIII. Cum privilegio. [1534]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Christopher Saint German.</note>
                  <note>Caption title reads: Of dyuers abusyons concernynge some of the seven sacraments, and dyuers other thynges.</note>
                  <note>Errata on recto of k3, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>An answer to:  More, Sir Thomas.  The apologye of syr T. More knyght (STC 18078).</note>
                  <note>Answered by: More, Sir Thomas.  The debalacyon of Salem and Bizance (STC 18081).</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some leaves stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4934:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4934:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>THE AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DICIONS OF SALEM AND BYZANCE.</p>
            <p>LONDINI IN AEDIBVS THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAE BERTHELETI REGII IMPRESSORIS. ANNO DO. M.D.XXXIIII<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cum priuilegio.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:4934:2"/>
            <head>The introduction.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>ISAN.</speaker>
               <p>I haue many tymes ſith the makyng of our fyrſt dialoge, which is called Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem &amp; Byza<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, remebred the Articles of the treatiſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is called the tretiſe, concernyng the Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon betwixt the ſpiritualtie &amp; the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltie, whiche was the verye occaſion of makynge of our ſayd fyrſt dialoge: And I thynke verily, that yf the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that be recited in the ſayde trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe and other lyke, were refourmed, great peace and quietnes wold ſhortly folowe amonge the people. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou woldeſt my frende Salem, to encorage them that haue good zeale towarde a refourmation of ſuche abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, take the peyne to recyte ſome mo thynges, that be myſuſed, and ouer that woldeſt deuiſe ſome meanes howe they myght alſo be reformed: I thynke it wolde do greatte good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall my frende Byzance with good wyll do that in me is to accomplyſſhe thy deſyre.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:4934:2"/>
            <head>¶Of dyuers abuſyons concernynge ſome of the ſeuen ſacramentes, and dyuers other thynges, as here after foloweth. The fyrſte Chapytre.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>AL.</speaker>
               <p>Many curates haue taken vppon them to ſaye, that they be not bounde to miniſter the ſacramentes to the people, onles they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and that ſpeciallye the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of extreme vnction, whiche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is called anoyllynge. And yet the truthe is, that they are bounde to gyue a great diligence therto them ſelf, and ſpecially to admonyſhe theym that be aboute the ſycke perſone, that they may haue knowledge when nede ſhall require. And therfore if any dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that ſacrament for lacke of ſuche good diligence of the curate, ſurely it is in hym a great offence.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> ¶Alſo it hath ben a great default in many places, that the curates wyll not
<pb facs="tcp:4934:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſynge maſſe nor dirige for none of their paryſhens at theyr buryals, no more than they wyll do for ſtraungers that dyed within the paryſſhe, excepte they haue money for theyr labour, for ſythe they haue of theyr paryſhens theyr ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, offrynges, and dyuers other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytes and commodities, as curates cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomably haue: Charitie wolde that they ſhulde burye them eſpecially that be houſeholders, and theyr chylderne with dirige and maſſe freely, without takynge any thynge for it: but to ſaye maſſe and dirige for ſtraungers they be not bounde therto, but of their charite. But yet to bury all them frely that dye within the paryſhe they are bounde of duetie to do it.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo it is greatte trouble and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the people in many places, that the ſacrament of confirmation is taken fro the propre curates, and is gyuen only to byſhoppes. For therby the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ſome places be many tymes put to greatte labours and expences in gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4934:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> attendaunce to the byſſhoppes. And alſo many chylderne be therby in ſome countreyes longe vnconfyrmed, and ſometyme dye without it: where if the curates myght confyrme theym, as they myght fyrſte, they ſhulde be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmed with leſſe labour, and be in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che more greater ſuertie to haue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament then they be nowe. And ſythe byſhoppes haue taken that auctoritie to them ſelfe, and no greatter conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration apperynge why they ſhulde do ſo then there dothe: It myght happely cauſe ſome ſymple men to eſteme, that there is not ſuche neceſſitie in that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament as there is in dede. For they may happely thinke, that if there were, the byſhops wolde not put the children in ſuche ieoperdie to be ſo longe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, as they be ofte by that occaſion, and no greatter cauſe to moue them to it then they thynke there is.</p>
               <p>¶The prohybitinge alſo of byſſhops to graunt pardons hath letted greatly the deuocyon to pardons, and the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge
<pb facs="tcp:4934:4"/> of money for herynge of confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and ſpecially at pardons, hathe alſo done right great hurt. For there is a ſayeng, the mo confeſſions, the great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter profyt. Wherby it is ment, that the profyte in heryng confeſſions is moche regarded. And that hath made many tymes ryght ſhort confeſſions, and alſo as light &amp; as haſty abſolutions, which perauenture hath made ſome vnware and vnlerned perſons to haue the leſſe regarde to be confeſſed.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> ¶And why ſhuld the power of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution that was gyuen by Chriſte to all prieſtes: be generally taken from them in any caſe, and ſpecially from curates that be admytted to be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to haue cure of ſoules, and be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted only to byſhops or to theyr deputies, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties percaſe be not many tymes ſo ſufficient as the curates be, fro whome it is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo that it ſemeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the power of priſtes is reſtrayned in that behalfe by the lawe of man without cauſe reſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable, and wolde therfore be reformed.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:4934:4"/>
                  <hi>6.</hi> ¶Alſo it wolde be playnly declared, where the curate may prohibite his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhens to be houſeled &amp; where not. And ſurely it ſemeth not to ſtand with chari<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if a paryſhener at the tyme of his houſelyng lacke money to pay his due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that he ſhuld be therfore prohibit of houſelynge. And ſure it is, that great grudges haue enſued in tymes paſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuche matters. A prieſte (if he wyl) may go to maſſe, though he be in deed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſynne, and no manne can prohibite hym: but if the curate onely by coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thynke his paryſſhener in deedly ſynne, he wyll prohibite him.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7.</hi> ¶Alſo curious buildynges of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall men, and the apparel therof, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſometyme be apparelled with vaine ſtories, ſtereth more theym that behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it to vanitie and to a worldly loue, then to any mekenes or deuotion. And though it be right conuenient, that by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and other ſpirituall rulers haue conuenient dwellyng places after their degree, yet all wolde be ordered to the
<pb facs="tcp:4934:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> honour of god, and to the good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the people.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo it diminyſheth the deuocion of prieſtes greattely in many places, that there haue ben ſo many chapplens and ſeruynge prieſtes. For they that be vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally conuerſant amonge laye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and be bounde to obſerue worldely attendaunce as lay men are, can neuer haue their minde ſo perfitly to prayer &amp; deuotion, as they that be curates, or be continually reſident in churches. For lyke as there is a mery prouerbe in pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of courte, that the very walles tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the lawe, and that euerye buſſhe in the countrey teareth away a pece: ſo it maye be ſaide, that the very walles of the churche teache deuotion, and that worldly company driueth it awaye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geyne. And whenne they be in youthe brought vp in ſuche worldly company, it wyll be harde for them in age to ſette their mynde to prayer and contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And ſurely if lay menne wolde be contented for preſeruynge of deuotion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4934:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> in prieſtes to forbeare the ſeruyce and familyaritee of theym more then they haue done in tyme paſt, and wolde here maſſe and diuine ſeruice, whenne they myghte conueniently at their paryſſhe churches, at the leſte on holydays, and when they may here none, wold ſupply it with prayer or ſome other good wer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, they ſhulde more pleaſe almyghty god therby, and more ſhewe them ſelfe to honour the ſacrament then they doo nowe, whan they here maſſes of theyr chappleyns at home.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo it hath bene a great ouerſighte (as it ſemeth) in the clergie, that they haue made ſo ſtrayte lawes of irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larite as they haue done. For it is hard for any prieſte to eſchewe them all. And thervppon it foloweth that whan they falle into ſuche irregularitie, and can not by and by be diſpenſed with (for there is none at hande that hathe that power) then neuer the leſſe bicauſe they ſhuld not be noted, they yet ſyng maſſe as they dyd before. And that bryngeth
<pb facs="tcp:4934:6"/> ſome prieſtes into ſuche a largenes of conſcience, that they be the bolder to do lykewyſe in other thynges: and ſo by contynuall cuſtome therin can lerne to lyue quietly in an euyll conſcience.</p>
               <p>Wherfore it were better, that irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in ſome poyntes were clerely put away, than to driue them in euery light poynt to ſeke for diſpenſations. For ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny men thynke, that ſuch diſpenſations not only in that caſe, but in many other alſo, ſerue rather for gettynge of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney than for increaſynge of vertue.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10.</hi> ¶And there is ſuch a lyke thyng in religion. For they profeſſe the olde ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, whiche although there be alſo ſome diſpenſations very ſtrayte to be kepte in theſe dayes, bycauſe the people be not vniuerſally ſo ſtronge now as they were at the makynge of the ſayde ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. And when they ſee the reules day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broken afore theym, as well in other as in them ſelfe without correction, it bryngeth in to theym a quiete harte in an euyll conſcience, a boldenes to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4934:6"/> and fynally a cuſtome in ſynne: wherby folowe many euyll examples to the people: and yet they that doo it, wyl be called holy and perfite. And ſure it is, that it were better to haue an eaſy rule well kept, than an harde rule bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken without correction.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11.</hi> ¶Alſo it is a thyng greatly abuſed, that clerkes do clayme to haue as high power, and as moche lybertie in theyr poſſeſſions &amp; goodes, as lay men haue in theirs. For the truth is, that they may take of the goodes that they haue for their miniſtration, but onely a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſuſtentation for theym ſelfe, and for a conuenient ſuſtenaunce for their houſeholde, and the reſydue they are bounde to diſtribute amonge the pore. And in this poynte the lawe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme is ouermoche fauourable to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall men. For it ſuffreth them to make theyr wylles and bequeſtes of theyr goodes, how ſo euer they come to them by tythes, oblacyons, or otherwyſe, as lyberally as any laye manne maye.
<pb facs="tcp:4934:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> And thoughe that be agaynſte the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, yet the clergie of this realme, per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyuynge howe fauourable the lawe of the realme is to theym in that poynte, hath made a conſtitution prouinciall, accordynge to the lawes of the realme, that no man ſhall hynder or let the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the ſame. And ſurely both the ſayd lawes wold be reformed. For they haue ben a right ſpecial cauſe, as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, that hath made ſo many to gruge at the goodes &amp; poſſeſſions of the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie as there hath done.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo many prieſtes fynde defaulte that ſome preſtes be in extreme neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and haue nothynge to releue them ſelfe with, whiche is not as they thynke conuenient to be ſuffered in prieſtis: but they regarde but lyttell the pouertie of ſome lay manne. Our lorde was pore hym ſelfe: and his diſciples, to whome prieſtes be ſucceſſours, were poore alſo, and yet ſomme prieſtes wene, that it is not conuenient for any of them to be in pouertie. I beſeche our lorde ſende vs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4934:7"/> many that be ryche in vertue and pore in ſpirite, and then the worldly pouerte ſhalbe the more eſely borne. I haue red of ſome byſhops, that haue made ſuche ꝓuiſion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no preſt ſhuld go abeggyng within his dioces, but I haue not red of any ſuch prouiſion for lay men. But if ſome prouiſion were made to releue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great multitude of poore men that be nowe in extreme neceſſite, I trow fewe thinges were more neceſſary to be gone about. And ouer that if any preſte be in ſuche extreme pouertie as they ſpeake of, it is moſte ſpecially through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faute of ſpirituall men, for they haue diuiſed titles for prieſtes in ſuche ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that they be of none effecte in the lawes of the realme: And the cauſe ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of is, for they aſke not counſaylle ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of them that be lerned in the ſayd la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, ne as it ſemeth wyll not obeye the kynges lawe in that behalfe, but make them titles after the groundes of other lawes. And therfore prieſtes many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes were as good to be without theyr
<pb facs="tcp:4934:8"/> titles as to haue theym in ſuche maner as they haue nowe.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13.</hi> ¶Alſo if the moſte honeſt and moſt ſubſtanciall curates and prieſtes in the countrey were examined, what increace of vertue hath ryſen by viſitations and ſcenes, as they haue bene of late vſed: It wolde appere vppon that examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that lyttell or none hath folowed therby, but that the clergye &amp; ſome lay men alſo appere there, and pay certain dueties, and then do after as they dyd before. And that the moſte lighteſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in all the precincte of the viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by meanes of rewardes, ſhalbe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu as they were wont to do. And ſyth the hole clergie haue ſubmyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theym to the kynges grace. It ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that he hathe good auctoritie to examyne, howe ſuche viſitacyons be vſed, and to ſette theym in ſuche or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that vertue therby maye hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be increaſed, and vice repelled and putte awaye. And I ſuppoſe verayly, that his grace is bounde in conſcience
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4934:8"/> to loke ſpecially vppon it.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14.</hi> ¶More ouer euen now of late ſyth the ſtatute made in the .xxi. yere of the reygne of oure ſoueraygne lorde the kyng that nowe is, ageynſt pluralities and none reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, is riſen this policy, that a prieſt that intendeth not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, or that intendeth to haue mo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefyces than the prouiſyon of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute waranteth hym to haue: wyll la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſome lorde ſpirituall or tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to be his chappleyne, nothyng pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſynge to do hym ſeruice, and the lord lyke wiſe nothynge deſyrynge his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: and knowyng alſo the entent why he dothe it, wyll accept hym to his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plen, and ſo wylfully defraude the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute: Is this troweſt thou my frende Byzance no offence in the lorde and in the chappleyne?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶<hi>BIZAVNCE.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I thynke verily yes, and that the offence is greatter in the chappleyne thenne in the lorde, yf there be no cauſe reaſonable why he dothe hit. And thoughe hit be more offence
<pb facs="tcp:4934:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the chappleyne, yet is hit no lyttelle offence in the lorde, that ſo wylfullye breaketh the intent and prouiſion of ſo good a ſtatute. For the prouiſo of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tute was made, bicauſe it was thought reaſonable, that lordes ſpirituall and temporall ſhulde haue chappleynes to do them ſeruice: but here no ſeruice is regarded. And ſurely by ſuche meanes and other lyke, ſome prieſtes haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny benefyces, where an other good ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prieſt, that is better worthy to haue a cure then he, hath neuer one.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo thoughe the people be more prone and be ſoner moued to go on pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gremages, to bye belles, or veſtemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or to gyue money for trentals, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of chauntries, kepynge of obi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, maynteynynge proceſſions and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che other outward dedes, wherby ſome worldely recreation or worldely laude and prayſe, or ſom good familiar chere and worldly thanke maye folowe, then they be to releue pore folkes that haue nede, wherby moſte commonly neyther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4934:9"/> worldly prayſe ne other worldly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie foloweth, ſpecially if it be ſecretly hyd in the boſome of the poore man, as it oughte to be: yet do not prechers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the people to releue their pore neyghbours that haue nede, as they ought to do: but ſuffre them to lye ſtyll in ſuche outward dedes, as though all were wel, when it is ryght farre amys. The nature of man is moche inclyned to be lauded and prayſed, and therfore the people wolde be continually inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that ſuch laude diminiſheth gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the rewarde that they ſhulde haue of god for theyr good dedes. And they ſhoulde be inſtructed alſo, that what good dede ſo euer they do, they oughte to truſt more in the grace and goodnes of god then in the dede, howe great ſo euer it be. Howe be it in whoſe default it is, that it hath not ben ſo in late tyme paſte, I wyll not ſpeke of at this time, but commytte it to other: but through whoſe default ſo euer it hath bene, yf it coulde yet be refourmed and broughte
<pb facs="tcp:4934:10"/> into due courſe, it were right expedient, and nothynge more then it were. I red ones a narration, that there was a pore ſycke man that lay bedred, and had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge to ſuccour hym ſelfe with all, whervpon a neyghbour of his ſeynge his extreme neceſſitie, moued with pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, appoynted one of his ſeruantes to ſee hym haue meate and drynke at cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne houres, as nede required, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the poore man was greatly releued a longe ſeaſon. So it hapned that on a tyme the ſeruaunt that was wonte to bryng hym meate, had buſynes, ſo that he myght not come at the houre accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed: Wherfore the poore man was very angry bothe with the mayſter and with the ſeruant, ſayenge, they had no pitie on theyr poore neyghboure, and that if they were in like caſe as he was, they wold be lothe to be ſo ſerued them ſelfe, and prayed our lorde, that or that they dyed, they myghte feele the peyne that he felte. with thoſe wordes the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant came with meate. And yet the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4934:10"/> of the man was ſo greatte, that he coulde not forbeare, but that he ſpake lyke wordes to the ſeruaunt. Then the ſeruant was angrye and ſayde, that he ſawe well, that his maiſter and he both had loſte al their coſte and labour, and ſo not contented with the pore man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and tolde his mayſter all the matter, and that he thought it were wel done, that he ſhoulde lette hym alone, tyll he coulde mekely yelde hym than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes for his good dede. The maſter an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſayd: I do not that I doo for any thanke that I loke for of hym that I gyue it to, and ſythe he gyueth vs no thankes for it, our rewarde ſhall be the more of god. And ſo he cauſed his ſeruaunt to doo as he hadde done before.</p>
               <p>¶But yet though this manne toke it thus charitably, it is verye lyke that mooſte other men wolde in ſuche caſe haue withdrawen their good dede. And ſurely ſuche chances wyll fall among, if men ſhulde ſet their myndes moche
<pb facs="tcp:4934:11"/> to releue poore men. As if a man lent money to a poore man at his nede, and at the daye he aſketh his money, hit myght happe that yf he aſked it twyſe, that ſome poore man wolde ſaye, that he was very haſty in the aſkynge, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge no nede to it, with ſuche other vnſittyng wordes. And wolde not this happely diſcourage ſome man to lende money to other poore men in their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie? I trowe yes, and yet it ſhulde not be ſoo. Therfore ſuche demeanour wold be moche reproued in poore men. And the ryche men wolde be alſo coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayled not to withdrawe their good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des after their power for ſuche demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, whiche in dede increaſeth theyr rewarde greattely before god. And yf preachers dyd encourage the people to ſuffre ſuche thynges al that they coude, and yet ſome men wolde be the more ſlacke to helpe other poore men for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che demeanour: howe wyll it be then thynkeſt thou, if men be nothynge en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged nor putte in mynde of ſuche
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4934:11"/> ſufferaunce, but be comforted as welle by ſecrete counſell in confeſſion as by preachynge to gyue money for ſowles inpurgatorie, or in ſuche other maner as before apperethe, as thoughe that ſhulde ſuffyſe vnto them? wyl not then the Charitie to theyr neyghbours be lyghtly forgotten, though it be vndou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly the beſte? It is no doubte but it wyll. And well I wote, that in the time of that, that is nowe called the olde ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholycal preachyng, the Charite to our neyghbours is nigh forgoten, &amp; the abu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſions concernyng ꝓdons, pilgrimages, purgatorie, pompous buryals, tythes, offerynges, and ſuche other, haue be meruaylouſly multiplyed and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and yet I haue harde but of very fewe in compariſon, that haue loked to the reformation of it, our lorde amende it, when his wyll ſhall be. Amen.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16.</hi> ¶Alſo many prechers in tyme paſt haue tourned a great parte of the tale to the mayntenaunce of the lybertie of the church, to the honour of preeſthod,
<pb facs="tcp:4934:12"/> to feare the cenſures of the churche, though they be gyuen withoute cauſe, and to obey al lawes made by the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and to doo as prieſtes doo teache, and not as they doo, ſuffyſeth to laye menne: and ſuche other lyke, that the people haue myſlyked greately. And whan religious men haue preched, they haue moche perſwaded ſuche thynges, as haue ben for their ſyngular profite and commoditie, ſo moche that it hathe rather diminiſſhed the deuotion of the people then increaſed it. And therfore I am farre deceyued, but that the moſt parte of all the defautes and diſcordes that be nowe in the temporaltie, haue ryſen through the defaut of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie. But yet I meane not that al ſuch diſcordes be ryſen by the defaute of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall menne, that be nowe lyuynge. For vndoubtedly they were begonne before theyr tyme by theyr predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours: but yet my meanynge is, that the ſpirituall menne that nowe be, are bounde before any other to helpe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4934:12"/> ſuche thynges al that they can: And I truſte that there be many diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſo to do, if they had helpe.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17.</hi> ¶Alſo it is a greatte ouerſyghte, that prieſtes accompte a defaute in one prieſte to ſownde to the rebuke of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prieſte, bycauſe they be all of one order. And that yet they go not about to reforme them that ſo offende. And ſo it is lykewiſe of religious menne: and they gruge more in their hartis ageinſt hym that maketh an euyl report of one, that is of the ſame degree that they be of, though it be trewe, than they do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte theym that make an euyll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of an other, that is not of the ſame degree that they be of, though it be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true. And ſurely that is a great defaut, and many great inconueniences folow vpon it, that I wyll not ſpeke of now. And there is no reaſon why they ought ſo to take it, ſyth the defaut of one preſt is no more reprofe to an nother, thenne the defaulte of one lay manne or laye womanne is to an nother.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:4934:13"/>
               <speaker>BYZANCE.</speaker>
               <p>It is trewe in dede as thou ſayſte, but yet the thyng that moſt myſ lyketh prieſtes and religiouſe men in ſuche reportes, is that they take it to be ſpoken to the reproche of all prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes or religious, and ſo ſome wyll ſaye in dede, that it is a ſhame to al prieſtis.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>If any man ſay ſo, he is far ouerſene. And prieſtes that be the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes and lyght of the worlde, ought moſte ſpecially before any other to take pacience at ſuche thynges, and rather to deſyre, that the prieſte that is repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, might come to reformation, then to take the matter as though it pertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to them ſelfe. And veryly the truth is, that a defaulte in a laye man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſoundeth mooſte commonly more to the reprofe of prieſtes, than doth the defaute of one preſte to an other: onles he be a ſpeciall occaſyon therof hym ſelfe. For prieſtes are more bounde to lay men then commonly one prieſte is to an other. For they haue their lyuing of lay men, and are therby more ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4934:13"/> bounde by a dewe order of charitie to procure their helth of body and ſoule before other that they haue no ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyt of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>yea but the lyuyng that a prieſt hath is moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly but of ſome particular laye men, that are but fewe in nombre as in compariſon. And when he hath done his duetie to them agayn to pray for them, &amp; doth for them as his dutie requireth, then is he neuer a whit bounden to other lay men that he hath no profite by, but is then bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den more to an other prieſte, that is of the ſame order that he is of, and that is alſo in a more perfyte way of lyuynge than lay men be, then he is to other lay menne. And oughte therfore to myſlyke more an euyll reporte of a prieſte, then of a lay man, and ſo ought laye men to doo lyke wiſe, if they wolde folowe the due ordre of charitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>As to that reſon a ſeculer preſt were more bounden to be diſcontented with an euyll reporte of a monke or a frere then of a ſeculer preſt, for they be prieſtis as he is, and are in
<pb facs="tcp:4934:14"/> a more perfyte eſtate then he: and yet the common experience proueth, that they are not ſo, but rather be oft tymes ryght well contented, to here an euylle report of religious men, and they lyke wyſe of them, and therfore the truth is, that the affection that one prieſte hath to an other in ſuche caſe, is of a proude ſyngular loue that he hath to hym ſelf: rather then of a charitable loue to other prieſtes. And here it may be conſidered, howe far we be fro the charitie of ſaynt Paule, when he ſayd, ad Gal. iii. There is no iewe, there is no greke, there is no bondma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there is none fre, there is no male, there is no female, as who ſayth, the charitable man ſettith no difference betwyxte countrey and countrey, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twyxte ſtate and ſtate, ne betwyxte kynde of male or female. For as it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in the ſayde texte, we all be one in Chriſte, that is to ſaye, we chriſten men ought to loue eche other in Chriſt, of what degree or condycion ſo euer we be. And ſurely laye menne do thus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4934:14"/> to ſpirituall menne, and many tymes loue a prieſte, a monke, or a frier bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a lay man: but they wyll not commonly do ſo agayne, onleſſe ſome profytte or commoditie comme to them therby, our lorde amende it, whanne it pleaſeth hym. Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIZ.</speaker>
               <p>I pray the procede nowe to ſome other matter. <hi>18.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>It is alſo a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faut in many ſpirituall men, that they haue made pretence, that the tenth part belongethe to prieſtes by the lawe of god, for by that pretence all cuſtomes preſcriptions of none payment of any thyng that is tythable, though the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate haue ſufficient beſyde, are clerely diſalowed in ſpirituall courtes, and yet though ſomme queſtion be nowe late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly riſen, whether the tenth parte be due by the lawe of god or not, no man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoureth hym ſelfe to ſette the matter in a clerenes, but ſuffreth it and dyuers other thynges alſo to reſt ſtyll in doute as they haue done in tymes paſt. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtatute of .xlv. E. iii. commonly
<pb facs="tcp:4934:15"/> called the ſtatute of <hi>Silua cedua,</hi> whiche is taken by many ſpirituall men to be ageynſt the lawe of god: wolde be ſene, and if it be ageynſte the lawe of god, then it wold be broken, and if it be not, then it wolde be confyrmed, and ferther be prohibite that none vppon a peyne ſhal ſay ſo herafter. For if it be ſuffred to ſtande ſtyll as it doth nowe, vndonted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly great variaunce and expences wyll folowe thervpon hereafter. And ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall men are ſpecially bounde to doo that in them is to put ſuch thynges out of argument, and to ſet ſuche matters in ſuche a cleretie, that it ſhall appere, that they wolde not take one peny of the people for theyr ſpirituall miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more then they oughte to doo of ryghte. And that they ſeke rather the helth of their ſoules, then any lucre of their goodes.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19.</hi> ¶Alſo it is a right great ouerſight that in matters concernynge temporall thinges, and wherof the ſpiritual court may yet after the cuſtome nowe vſed in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4934:15"/> this realme holde plee, that they wyll iudge therin after the lawe ciuile or canon, and not after the lawe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme as they are bounde to do, and that vpon no leſſe peyne then vpon the peyn of reſtitution, and yet they do not thus vpon the preſcription of tythes, but fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe a ſpeciall preſcription deuiſed by them ſelf, which in this realme byndeth not ne gyueth no ryghte. And in lyke wyſe it is if a man by his wyll bequeth to one an other mans hors, this bequeſt after the lawes of the realme is vtterly voyde, for no manne after the lawes of the realme, maye lawfully gyue or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queth that is not his, and yet in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall court, they iuge the bequeſte to be good after this maner: that he to whom the bequeſte is made ſhall haue the value of the horſe, and ſurely ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they bynde them ſelfe to reſtitution, and ſo it is of the age of infantes and many other thynges, wherin the lawes do vary, wherof I wyl no farther ſpeke at this tyme.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4934:16"/>
                  <hi>20.</hi> ¶Alſo it is a greatte ouerſyghte, that ſuch thynges as at the begynning of the churche were refuſed by many ſpirituall men, bycauſe they thoughte they wolde lette and diminiſhe their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotions towarde god and goſtely thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, be nowe ſo vniuerſally accepted and vſed by them that be of the ſame or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der and degree that they were, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed them, but the particular hurtes and offences of conſciences that haue folowed vpon that doinge, I wyll not touche at this tyme.</p>
               <p n="21">
                  <hi>21.</hi> ¶Aſo it is a great ouerſight in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny religious men, that they wylle pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende, that the wey of their religion is the ſureſt way to ſaluation, and ſurely it wolde be prohibited, that no man v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon great peyne ſhulde hereafter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſay ſo. <hi>22.</hi> ¶Alſo this poynte hath done great hurte, that men wyll ſo lyghtly reporte as they do, that there be many heritikes, yea and they that be of that appetite to haue it ſo noiſed, vſe this polici to ſay that heritikes wil firſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4934:16"/> cauſe ſmal heriſies to be ſpro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abrode, to the intent they maye after brynge in greatter, and by tho wordis (gretter he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies) they meane that ſome men be of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that feith ſuffiſith without good werkes, and that they wolde haue all thinges in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, whiche if they coude bring about, it were in dede as they ſay a plain diſtruction of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth, &amp; they wyll affirme ſtiffely, that if they be ſuffred to continue, they wyll in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion bring it about. And how peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous a ſpeakynge that is, it is euident, for there can no man tell, whom it tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth: and therfore it may lightly cauſe great gruge in the hartes of many peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple. And as the truth is, it hath done ſo alredy. And nowe as to thoſe two arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles I wil ſay thus farre therin, that in good faith I knowe none that holdeth opinion, that good werkes be not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to ſaluacyon, ſpecially in men that haue full vſe of Reaſone, ne yet that all thynges oughte to be in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. ¶And I ſuppoſe verayly,
<pb facs="tcp:4934:17"/> that there is noted to be a greatter va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance in tho poyntes and in dyuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo, then there is in dede, yf the very intent of the parties were perfyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowen, and if it be ſo, then is there a gretter defaut in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wyl ſo light<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly iuge other to be heritikes, then there is in them that they note to holde thoſe diuerſities of opinions.</p>
               <p n="23">
                  <hi>23.</hi> ¶Alſo what a great abuſion is it in many ſpirituall men, as well religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as other, whyche be ſpecially or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned for the mayntenance of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of god, that they kepe in their han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des paſtures and groundes, which ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme were townes or villages inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with people, whiche righte moche maynteyned the ſeruice of god, and ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny of them kepeth in their handes alſo, parkes for fedynge of wylde beaſtes, that myght ryght well be made the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of Chriſten people, and that in great nombre: and thus they that moſt ſpecially ought to maynteyne the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of god, and increaſe his ſeruice,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4934:17"/> greatly decay it, diſtroy the people, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the power of the kynge and of the realme, and delay the repayring of the falle of aungelles verye moche, and though ſome temporall men haue ſuch paſtures and parkes as welle as ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall men haue: yet the greatter defaut in the kepynge therof is in ſpiritualle menne, and therfore haue I ſpoken of theym fyrſte.</p>
               <p n="24">
                  <hi>24.</hi> ¶Alſo there gothe a common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte abrode amonge the people, that ſpirituall men be moſt commonly more harde and ſtrayt in makyng of leaſſes, retynge of rentes, leuyenge of fynes, takynge of heriottes, allowynge of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations, alowyng of fees to offycers and ſuche other, then any lay men be. And as it is ſayd, they take occaſion to do ſo vnder pretence, that all that they do is for mayntenance of prayers, and of the ſeruice of god, ſoo that hit is in goddis quarell all that they doo. And therfore if they take any ſuite for any ryght that they clayme, or that any ſute
<pb facs="tcp:4934:18"/> be taken ageynſte them, they are moſte commonlye more extreme and ferther froo a meane waye, thenne any laye menne be.</p>
               <p>¶And this doth great hurt, &amp; maketh the people to gruge ageynſt them, and to eſteme great parcialitie and couetyſe in them, and ſo wyll it do as longe as it continueth, let them cloke it vnder the colour of goddis quarelle all that they can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>They muſte nedes ſue for their right, and alſo defende it. For els it myght happen, that they in proces of tyme ſhoulde haue but a lyttell to lyue with. And ſuche a reporte as thou ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt of maye lyghtely go abrode with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, and therfore they maye not leeſe theyr ryghte for ſuche exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>As the common prouerbe is trewe, that there is neuer ſmoke withoute ſomme fyre, ſo is hit trewe, that this reporte is not ryſen withoute ſomme cauſe, thoughe pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture the cauſe be not ſo greatte as the reporte is.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:4934:18"/>
               <p>¶And trouthe it is as thou ſayſt, they muſt nedes few for theyr ryght, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo defende hit. And I agree well, that it is very harde alſo to knowe, where a manne is extreme in his ſuytes, and where he is extremely handeled, and therfore I trowe the beſte remedy were for theym to diſpoſe theym ſelfe in doubtefull thynges rather to be ouer ſufferable.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <hi>25.</hi> ¶Alſo it hath ben a righte greatte ouerſyghte in tyme paſte, that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie of the bodye hathe bene more myſlyked in theym that ſhoulde be admytted to be prieſtes, thanne the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formytie of lyfe, or lacke of moralle vertues, or of lernynge. For yf he be perſonable, the lacke of ſuche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as hit is ſayde, be ſoone paſſedde ouer, as thowghe the goodlyneſſe of the perſonne ſhoulde ſounde to the honour of pryeſtehoode, but ſurelye hit is Mekenes and Charytie, that brynge to pryeſtes the veraye trewe honour.</p>
               <p n="26">
                  <pb facs="tcp:4934:19"/>
                  <hi>26.</hi> ¶Alſo if it were well conſydered, there are fewe ceremonies of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, but that they ſounde either to a pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eminence or els to a profyte of prieſtes, and that hath cauſed ſome perſones to fynd defaut at ſuch ceremonies, whiche as farre as euer I coulde perceyue, be of them ſelfe right good as to the moſt parte, if they were handled with meke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the mynyſters, as they ſhuld be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>But I praye the what be thoſe cerimonies, that they meane of?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>They meane of crepynge to the croſſe, and of the diſciplins afore Eaſter, that the bryde muſte be gyuen to the prieſte, and that the brydegrome muſte kyſſe the prieſte, of the halowynge of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delles, churches, ymages, and belles, and of the beryng of candelles on Can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>delmas day, of ſenſynge the myniſters at certayne feaſtes, of lyghtynge a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell before the Goſpell, or els not to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cede any farther, ne that none ſhall ſay Dominus vobiſcum, but he be within holy orders, and of dyuers other moo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4934:19"/> then I can remembre nowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>All theſe be good and commendable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>I thynke they be. And yet many men wene, that if there were no money of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred at the crepyng to the croſſe, ne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney gyuen for halowynge of churches, images, and belles, that thoſe ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies wolde laſte but a whyle: and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly there be many that thynke, that there be ſometyme diuers ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies at maſſe, that were rather brought vp for an honour to the miniſters then of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or of the ſeruice of god. And therfore they ſay, that if leſſe worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly pompe then is many tymes vſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute the minyſtracyon of it, it wolde pleaſe our lord better, and be alſo more edifienge to the people then it is nowe.</p>
               <p n="27">
                  <hi>27.</hi> ¶Alſo byſhoppes that be canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed haue a propre common appoynted vnto byſſhoppes, and this Antyphon, <hi>Ecce ſacerdos magnus,</hi> is often in their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce. And kynges that be canonyſed haue moſte commonly the common ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propried to an abbot. And me thinketh
<pb facs="tcp:4934:20"/> that, that is not ordered, as it ſhoulde be. For as me ſemeth the clergy can not of congruence gyue no leſſe honour to a kyng then to a byſhop.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BI.</speaker>
               <p>The cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſyng of ſayntes, ne yet the ſeruice of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church profiteth nothing the ſaintes. And therfore it forceth lyttell what an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>typhan or commons they haue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEM.</speaker>
               <p>It is trewe as thou ſayeſte, but yet ſuche canoniſations and the ſeruice ordeyned vpon it, be occaſions to enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage theym that be of the ſame degree as they be: to deſyre lyke vertue as they hadde that be ſoo canonyſed, and ſythe the vertue in princis is mooſte neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the people and to the holle com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welthe before all other: it ſemeth ſomewhat to be meruayled, why ſuche canoniſations haue not ben ſo ordered, that they ſhulde encourage princis to vertue more ſpecially than any other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYSANCE.</speaker>
               <p>Pryncis glorifye theym ſelfe but lyttell, for the canoniſation of other prynces, ne care but lyttelle for the ſeruyce appoynted to theym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:4934:20"/>
               <speaker>SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>But yet ſomme ſpiritualle menne haue for theym ſelfe regarded ſuche thynges in tyme paſte ryght mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and me thynkethe alwaye, that they oughte to doo lykewyſe for kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and pryncis, yea and that more thenne for theym ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BISANCE.</speaker>
               <p>Well I perceyue nowe, that thy mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge is, that ſpirituall menne haue in ſuche canoniſations ben more diligent to canoniſe one of the ſame degree, that they be of, thanne any other, as byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of byſhoppes, prieſtes of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, and religious, of religious, and ſpecially ſuche as be of the ſame regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar order as they be. And yet though it be ſoo, it is no defaute in theym, as me ſemeth, but rather a prayſe: for it is an enuye for vertue, whiche is called pia inuidia, a meke enuye, and that is com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mendable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶ <hi>SALEM.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Enuye in vertue is commendable, as thou ſayſte, but an enuye, who maye haue his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue more knowen, or moore lawded
<pb facs="tcp:4934:21"/> and preyſed then other, is not commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable. And it is verye lyke that ſuche thynges haue ben ſene in ſome menne, concernyng ſuch canoniſations in time paſte, but in princis no ſuche affection can be iudged. For commonly leſſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is gyuen to princis that be cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſed, thenne to other, as it appereth of ſaynt Lucius that was the firſt kynge chriſtened of the Brytons in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, and of ſaynt Ethelbert, that was the fyrſte chryſten kynge of Englyſſhe men, whiche be but lyttel knowen, and haue but lyttell honour in compariſon of other, and that me thynketh is not well ordred.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BISAN.</speaker>
               <p>Well I perceyue thy mynde nowe in this mattier more perfitely then I dyd before, and nowe ſyth thou haſte ſpoken before of cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſations of ſayntes, I praye the lette me here thy mynde, to what intent they were fyrſte ordeyned, and who hathe auctoritie to make theym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>One cauſe why they were ordeyned, was to encreaſe vertue in other, ſpecially in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4934:21"/> theym that be of the ſame degre as they were, that be ſo canoniſed, as I haue ſayd before, and it hath ben moſte vſed for them that haue lyued a good and a bleſſed lyfe, aboue the common ſorte of other good chriſten menne, to gyue the people god example in prayer, faſtyng, and almes dede, in ſufferynge of tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and vexations for ryghtwiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes pacientlye, or ſuche other. And yf it pleaſe our lorde to ſhew myracles for him, wherby it appereth that he hath ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepted his good werkes, that is a thing moch neceſſary in ſuch canoniſations: An other cauſe of ſuche canoniſation hath ben alſo to eſchue ſciſmes &amp; varia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces among the people, when one wold worſhyp one as a ſaynte, and an other wolde ſay he were none. And in the cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pytre <hi>Extra de reliquijs. Ca. Audiuimus,</hi> It is ſayd, that thoughe myracles be done, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yet it is not lawfull to worſhyp any as a ſaynct without auctoritie of the ſee of Rome. But what auctoritie the ſee of Rome hath to make ſuche a canoniſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:4934:22"/> I neuer harde. Howe be it fyue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be made in the gloſe, <hi>De reliquijs et veneratione ſanctorum. Ca. vnico, Glorioſus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </hi> why the ſee of Rome ought to do it before all other.</p>
               <p>¶Fyrſte is, by cauſe the canonyſacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſaynctes is one of the greatteſte cauſes, that maye be pourpoſedde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge Chryſten people. The ſeconde is, that bycauſe myracles be aſcrybed to the feythe. Therfore this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſithe it is notably of the feithe, is to be referred to the ſee apoſtolyke. The thyrde, bicauſe it perteineth to the pope to open and declare the doutes of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, therfore of ſtronger reaſone he ought to open and declare the doubtes of holyneſſe. The fourthe is that hit oughte onely to belonge to the See of Rome, leeſte by the ſymplicitie of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny byſhoppes, the people ſhoulde hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be deceyued. The fyfte, leeſt the ſaynctes canonyſed ſhoulde be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to a nombre infinite. And ſoo ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by deuocyon waxe colde, and holyneſſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4934:22"/> lyttell ſette by. Theſe be the reaſons of the ſayde Gloſe, and as me ſemethe, they proue not the intente, that they be made for.</p>
               <p>¶ And as to one of the ſayde reaſons it is apparant, that it dothe not. For it is euident inough, that one byſſhoppe may ſooner be deceyued than many by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes: and all the reſydue of the ſaid reaſons I commytte to the iudgement of the reders. And where in the ſame gloſe, it is ſayd ferther, that if the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che erre in the canoniſation of a ſaynt, that yet it is not to beleue, that hit er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. Surely if the churche erre therin in dede, it is meruayle, why hit maye not be beleued that it erreth, for the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the is alway to be beleued, though ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyme after the lawe of man, a man may be ſtopped to ſaye the truthe, as hit is in dyuers caſes of eſtopelles, in the lawes of Englande, where a manne maye be eſtopped to ſaye, that he kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth verely is trew, but yet all though he be ſoo eſtopped to ſaye the trewthe,
<pb facs="tcp:4934:23"/> he may beleue therin as he lyſte, and ſo reaſon wolde he ſhulde do of ſuche ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſations. And therfore I thynke, that the meanynge of the ſayd gloſe is, that if the churche vpon vntrue profes canoniſe one that is no ſayncte in dede, that yet if a man wyll ſay, that he is no ſaynt, that he offendeth in that ſaying. For why, to ſay that he is no ſaynte, is is aſmoche to ſay, as that he is in hell, for all that be in heuen or pourgatorie be ſaynctes. For they in purgatorie be ſure of ſaluation, thoughe as ſomme holde opinion, they lacke the fruition of the godheed: and that therfore it is ryght good and charitable to pray that they may be brought to it.</p>
               <p>¶And then ſythe it is an offence to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme opinatiuely, that any perſon that is departed is in Helle, onles it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by ſcripture that it is ſo, as it is of Cayme, Iudas, and ſome other, more ſtronger he offendeth, that wyll opina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely ſaye, that he whome the churche hath canoniſed is in helle. But though
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4934:23"/> it be agreed, that it is an offence to ſay that he that the churche hath canoniſed for a ſaynt, is no ſaynt, yet why it ſhuld be heriſi to ſay he is no ſaint, ſith it may be true as he ſaith, and as the ſaid gloſe affirmeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be, I ſe no reſon. For they them ſelf that haue canoniſed him knowe not ne can not know aſſuredly, that he that is ſo canoniſed is in heuen, but that they haue a good truſte that he is ſo. For the wytneſſe maye deceyue them, as is ſaid before: And accordyng to the ſame effecte it is ſayde, <hi>Extra de ſenten. excommunicationis a nobis ſecundo,</hi> that the iugement of god is ſo knytte to the truthe, that it neuer deceyueth ne can not be deceyued, but the iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the church foloweth oft times the opinion of men, &amp; ſo it may be vntrue, &amp; deceiue, and alſo lightly be deceyued. And more ouer one of the principal intentes of ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che canoniſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, is when any opinion riſeth amonge the people, that ſuche a man is a ſaynt, and that ſome begyn to honour hym, and ſome haply ſaye they
<pb facs="tcp:4934:24"/> doo not welle to ſette the mattier in ſuche an order, that there ſhall be no ſciſmes thervppon amonge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But yf any opinion ryſe amonge the people, that any is holye and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and myracles be doone, than it is ſuffered, that the people maye honour theym, yf they be not prohybite by the ſuperiours, not withſtondynge the ſayde Chapitre <hi>Audiuimus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>¶And vnder this maner kyng Henry the ſyxte, and mayſter Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Shorn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſuffered to be worſhypped, which be not canonyſed. And what a canoniſation troweſt thou had the apoſtels, and ſuch other holy men, in the begynnynge of the churche?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BISAVNCE.</speaker>
               <p>I trowe none, but that the holy goſte wytneſſed in the hartes of all the people, that they were holy and bleſſed, and that ſuffiſed without any ferther canoniſation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEM.</speaker>
               <p>Surely it is as thou ſayſte, but of ſome other newe ſayntes, it hath not benne alwaye ſo, but whanne ſomme hath holden one veray holy, an other
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4934:24"/> hath douted at it. And therfore to kepe the people in a good quyetnes in that behalfe. Canonyſacyons haue benne made, not that the people ſhoulde be bounde therby to beleue their holynes, as to an artycle of the faythe, but to gyue theym occaſyon the rather to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree therin in one, ſythe ſo many great clerkes haue allowed the wytneſſe in profe of his holyneſſe, as there hathe doone.</p>
               <p>¶And therfore though it were admyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted that he were an herityke, that wold obſtinately holde opinyon, that the churche gathered to gether in the holye gooſte maye erre in a thynge that is of the fayth, &amp; that this is of the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, for as moch as the canoniſation of a ſayncte perteyneth to the Faythe, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in the inquery of his fayth, and of his moralle vertues, and of his doynge myracles ſtondethe all the mattier: hit maye be aunſwered, that the caſes be not lyke, for two cauſes.
<pb facs="tcp:4934:25"/> Firſt for that ſuch a canoniſation is not appoynted by the lawes to the holle clergie, ne to the generall counſell, but to the ſee of Rome onely, and vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly that ſee may erre, deceyue and be deceyued. For that ſee maketh not the churche. Seconde in ſuch a canoniſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it ſuffiſeth, if the wytnes affyrme, that he was a man of a true faith, with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out reherſynge all the articles of the faithe in ſpeciall. And therfore the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the articles of the faith foloweth not thervppon: And that the churche maye not erre in thynges that be of the faithe, I take it to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtonde, where any great dout ryſeth con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernynge the faith. And that, that dout is commytted to the churche: wherby I vnderſtonde mooſte proprely the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Counſayle, that they then may not erre. And therto I can ryghte well agree. For it is not to thynke, that our lorde that is the very truthe, wolde leue his people without a dewe meane how to come to knowlege of the truthe: for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4934:25"/> that wyll not leaue any one particular perſon in ſuche doubt, but that he may come to the knowledge of the truthe, yf he wyll fully put his truſt in hym. And therfore it is ſayd. <hi>2. par. xx. Cum ignore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, quid facere debeamus, hoc ſolum reſidui ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bemus, vt oculi noſtri ad te dirigantur,</hi> that is to ſay, Lorde when we be ignorant and wotte not what to do, this only remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to vs for our comfort, that we lift our eien vp to the, as who ſaythe, that ſuffiſeth vnto vs, ſo that we ſhall not erre. But in ſuche a canoniſatyon, though all the hole clergie dyd it, they might erre. For it is but mater in dede: and more ſtronger theſe of Rome may erre therin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>This maner of reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge is daungerous. For hit myghte lyghtely induce the people to ſette at nought the order and decrees of theyr ſuperiours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>As to that thou kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weſt well, that no man hath power to make lawes to bynd other, but he haue auctoritie therto of god. And yf it can be proued, that the clergie haue aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite
<pb facs="tcp:4934:26"/> of god to canoniſe a ſaint, and that they be all heritikes, that beleue it not, it muſt be obeyed, our lorde forbeade it ſhulde be otherwyſe. But if it can not be proued, that they haue that aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie by the lawe of god, but that they haue hit onely by a cuſtome and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of Princis, thenne the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of hit ſhall doo good to cauſe the matter be knowen as it is.</p>
               <p>And yet maye the ſayntes that in tyme paſte haue benne taken for holye and bleſſed, be ſtyll ſo taken.</p>
               <p>¶And thenne alſo ſhall hit not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for heryſye, that is none in dede: but the verye trewe intente of cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſations ſhalbe knowen.</p>
               <p>¶And I ſuppoſe farther, that it were no greatte mattier, whether any were canonyſed hereafter or not, yf the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wolde be quyete withoute it: and not be ſoo newe fangle to pylgryma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as ſomme haue benne in tyme paſte, and thenne to kepe the people in quieteneſſe and in good ordre in all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4934:26"/> thynges, kynges and princis are moſte ſpecyally bounden to before any other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYSANCE.</speaker>
               <p>Pryncis canne not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyne, who hathe a ryghte faythe, and who hathe not, ne what is a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, and what not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>¶SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>To examyne all the partycular artycles of the faythe, is not neceſſarye in Canonyſations, as I haue ſayde before, and what is a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, and whatte not, Pryncis and theyr counſaylles maye haue knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſufficiently: And therfore as me meth it pertayneth mooſte ſpecially to theym to order and appoynte ſuche ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonyſacyons atte a generalle Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaylle, rather then to any other, takyng the clergye to them as theyr counſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours in that behalfe. But for as moch as Princis haue in tyme paſt lyttell re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>garded ſuche ſmall matters, beyng oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed in more vrgent cauſes, for the common welthe, byſhops and ſpiritual rulers haue loked vpon ſuche canoniſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, whiche the people haue obeyed,
<pb facs="tcp:4934:27"/> and princis haue aſſented, and therin they haue done ryght well: and after by the long continuance and ſufferance they haue claymed, that they of ryght and none but they ought to do it: and yet haue they not only claymed that to the hole clergie, but haue ſo handeled the matter, that it hath bene broughte onely to the ſee of Rome to do it. And thervpon pretence hath ben made, that who ſo euer that ſee wyll appoynt to be taken as holy and bleſſed, ſhall be ſo taken vpon the peyne of heriſie, and to be taken as a ſciſmatike deuyded froo god, and his church, and whether that hath ben a great ouerſight, and a right great abuſion or not, it is apparant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>If one prince auctoriſed one as a ſaint, yet perauenture an other prince wold not ſo accept hym, and ſo it might happen to make variances betwixt the countreyes, when one wolde take one as holy and bleſſed, and the other not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>And therfore it were moſte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, that it ſhulde be done at a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4934:27"/> counſayle. And that princis and their ambaſſadours ſhoulde be therin iudges, takyng the ſpiritualtie as their counſaylours in that behalfe, as is ſaid before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIZ.</speaker>
               <p>If a man wolde ſay aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, that Peter and Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were not holye, I ſuppoſe hit were heriſie, why ſhuld it not be ſo likewiſe, when a ſaint is canonyſed: and the people hathe of longe tyme accepted hym for holy and bleſſed, be heriſie to ſay abidingly, that he were not holy ne bleſſed:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>To ſaye that Peter and Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or any other of the apoſtels were not holy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it were ageynſt ſcripture? For our lorde ſaid to the apoſtels, <hi>Luce. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </hi> I or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne to you as my father hath ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to me the kyngdom of heuen: that ye ſhall ſyt vpon my table in my kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, iugyng the .xii. tribus of Iſrael. No man therfore may ſay that the .xii. apoſtelles be not in heuen, but he ſaye ageynſt ſcripture. And ſo the very ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is a ſufficiente canoniſation for them. But it is apparant inough, that
<pb facs="tcp:4934:28"/> it is not ſo of other ſaintes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſed by ſcripture, though they haue by reſon of their holy life &amp; miracles be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accepted for ſaintes neuer ſo long. And therfore though a man, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wold ſay, that he that were ſo canoniſed, were not wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy to be canoniſid, did not wel, ne were not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended, bycauſe he went ſo far fro the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the people, &amp; of that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergie hath approued, yet it ſhuld ſeme not to be heriſy to ſay it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BI.</speaker>
               <p>what is it then to ſay, that a nother ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is not canoniſed, is as good &amp; as high in heuen, as Peter or Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>Surely it were a foule preſumption, &amp; a great ouerſight to ſaye it: but yet it were no hereſie. For it denieth not but that Peter &amp; Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be in heuen: and I truſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ar none of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> opinion. And if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of malice, &amp; to make a rumor amonges people, wyl report that there be certeyn perſons of that opinion, they offended right greuouſely therin. And ſurely ſuche reportes haue done great hurt, and wold be wel loked vpon here
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4934:28"/> after. For there be many ſo light of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that though the thing ſpoken be to the hurt of a right gret multitude of people, yet they wil anon report it ouer to other, not knowing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is true y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ſay <hi>.29.</hi> And now if thou wilt giue me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hering, I wyl ſhew the a litil of my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceite, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the chap. <hi>Oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s utrius<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xus,</hi> which is <hi>ex. de pen. &amp; ramiſſ.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BI.</speaker>
               <p>what thinkeſt thou of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chaptre?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>That it is not ſo reſonable in one point as me thinketh it ſhuld be, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for this cauſe: euery perſon man &amp; woman, after that he or ſhe comith to the yeres of diſcrecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal therby ſpecially ones in the yere be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed to theyr owne prieſt, wherby is vnderſtande theyr owne Curate: howe be it, it is decreed after in the ſame cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitre, that if a man vppon a iuſte cauſe wyll be confeſſed to an other prieſte: he ſhal fyrſt aſke lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his owne prieſte and opteyne it: for els the other prieſte (as it is ſayde there) maye nother looſe hym nor bynde hym. But it is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſedly declared in the ſayd chapitre,
<pb facs="tcp:4934:29"/> that yf a man vpon a iuſte cauſe aſke lycence of his propre prieſt to be ſhriuen in an other place, &amp; he of malice or fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes refuſeth to gyue hym licence, whether he may thervpon be ſhriuen at his liberte in an other place, &amp; ſom haue ſayde that in that caſe, the paryſhen is bounde to go to the ſuperiour, and that he may compelle the curate to gyue ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence. And ſome other haue ſayde, that the ſuperiour may in ſuche caſe giue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence him ſelfe. And many curates pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende the contrary, bycauſe the wordes of the ſayd chapitre be ſo generall, that lycence muſt be opteyned. And therfore they ſay in al caſes the paryſhens muſt be ſhriuen of their propre curates, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les the curat be content to gyue lycence to the contrary. And therfore for a more clere waye in conſcience in this behalfe, many paryſſhens haue in ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes paſte obteyned froo Rome, that they myghte choſe theym an able con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour, and a greatte multitude of ſuche lycences haue bene pourchaſed,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4934:29"/> as it is well knowen, whiche hathe be right great charge to the people in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places. And yet curates haue holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that not withſtondynge ſuche licences, religious men, bycauſe they be neyther elected by the people, ne appoynted by the byſhoppe, to haue the execution of a priſtes power ouer the peple, be none able confeſſours, and dyuers men haue ben of the ſame opinion. And therfore a ferther queſtion hath ben moued ther vpon, that if any religious men haue opteyned a priuilege, that they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne penaunce to the people, whether that then they be able confeſſours, ſo that they may laufully here the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an other mans paryſſhen, that hath ſuche a pardon, as is afore reher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and no lycence of his curate or not, and yet many curates haue ſayde nay. And the gloſe vpon the ſame chapytre, <hi>Omnis vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſexus,</hi> vpon theſe wordes, <hi>Alieno ſacerdoti,</hi> is of that opinion, as to the reder wyll appere.</p>
               <p>¶And by theſe diuerſities of opinions
<pb facs="tcp:4934:30"/> haue riſen great variances and ſtriues bytwixte curates and theyr pariſhens, where moſt loue and charitie ſhuld be, to the right great peryl and daunger of the ſoules of many perſons: &amp; it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray lyke ſo to do as longe as it ſhall be ſuffered to contynue as it dothe. It ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth therfore right expedient, that the rulers prouide a conuenyent remedye in this poynte, in as reaſonable time as they can.</p>
               <p>¶And ferthermore if ſpiritual reulers wolde now in this daungerous tyme, for the auoydyng of ſuche abuſions, as be here before remembred, and of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other here omytted, wherby great gruges haue ryſen in many parties of chriſtendom, be dylygent callers on to haue a generall counſaill, not onely to auoyde ſuche abuſions, but alſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyne, what power the clergie ought to haue, by the lawe of god, and what by cuſtome or by graunte of princis, and what not. And that they wolde be be contented to renounce all ſuche auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torite
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4934:30"/> as the ſayd counſail ſhuld thynke expedient to be renounſed: then it will appere, that they intende the honour of god, and welthe of the people. And if they wil indeuour them ſelf to defer the general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayl, &amp; reſiſte it to their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is a lykelyhod, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wyl do what they can, to maynteyne the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritie, power, &amp; worldly honour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue had in tyme paſte, without aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of it. And if it be ſoo, all princis chriſtened are bounde in conſcience to loke on it: and not to ceaſſe, tylle they haue by one aſſente refourmed, that is amyſſe in that behalfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIS.</speaker>
               <p>Perauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they wolde be the lother to ſuche a reformation, for it ſhuld ſhew a defaute in their predeceſſors, in that they wolde pretende to haue a power, where they had none: and that they wold alſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſuche thinges, which now be taken for abuſions.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>That pretence and ſuffera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was not begon by the biſhops that nowe be, and if they had, yet they ought not to po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der it ſo moch, but that
<pb facs="tcp:4934:31"/> they ſhoulde refourme it if they coulde, accordyng to this counſaile, that ſaith, that that we haue vnaduiſedly doone, let vs aduiſedly reforme ageyne. And yf they wyll do ſoo, I thynke veryly, they ſhall haue more true honour in the hartes of the people, then they haue had in tyme paſt. And it is not for ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall men moche to regarde ſuch tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poral honour. For they may more light<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly offende in acceptynge of it, than tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poral rulers. For they ſhulde euer ſtere the people by worde and by example to perfyte mekenes, and to diſpiſynge of all worldly pleaſures: and ſuch world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honours in ſpiritual men, breke that exaumple very moche. More ouer it is not verye lyke, that theſe grudges and murmurations that nowe be amonge chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl be appeſed, but it be by a general counſayl, or by battayle. And battaylle can be no reaſonable iuge in this caſe. For I here of no matter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is now in variance, but that it may right wel be determined by way of counſaile.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4934:31"/> And the people as far as euer I coulde perceyue, are moche deſyrous to here the determynation of the ſuperiours therin, &amp; redy to obey, and ar not incly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to any one opinion articuler or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo moch, but that they ar redy to be reformed: &amp; deſyre nothynge more then to knowe the truthe, and to haue perfit mekenes appere amonge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergi. Who may then in this caſe with out offence take the ſwerd, not aſſaying fyrſt, whether all myghte be appeaſed with Loue and Charitie withoute the ſwerde? I trowe no man wyll ſay that any man may do it. And ferthermore it appereth in a boke that is called <hi>Libellus de moribus Turcarum,</hi> that there be among the turkes foure dyuers opinions, who ſhall be ſaued, wherof the fyrſt opinion is of them that ſay, that no man maye be ſaued, but by the law of Mahumite. The ſeconde opinion is of theym, that ſaye the lawe of Mahumyte profiteth nothyng but the grace of god, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they ſay profiteth without lawe or
<pb facs="tcp:4934:32"/> merit. The .iii. opinion is of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſay that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe ſaued by his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit without law or grace. The .iiii. is of them that ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be ſaued in his own belefe, &amp; that there is gyuen to euery natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a law by god, in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he may be ſauid. And that no law is better tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other, how be it they that be of that opinion, be moche ſuſpected amonge the Turkes, and be taken as ſciſmatikes, and be greuouſely puny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, when they be found. And therfore they kepe theym ſelfe ſecrete, and dare not ſhew their opinion openly: but they that be of the other three opinions, be all of great multitude and power, and dare well auowe their opynion. And thervppon ryſeth many tymes greatte argumentes, variances, and debates, whiche ſometymes can not be appeſed without great battaylle. And therfore he that is ſtrengeſt hath his waye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred for the tyme. And theſe opinions can neuer be clerely determined amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge them, bicauſe they lacke a grounde to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4934:32"/> brynge them to the knowledge of the truth therin: for the boke of their lawe, which they call the Alkaron, is ſo ful of lyes and vayne trifles, that it bringeth them alwey that loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, into more doutes then they were before. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore theyr prieſtes be alway ſorye, when it ſhal be brought forth. For they know well, that the more it is loked vpon, the more the falſehode therof wyll appere. But we be all in an other caſe, for we haue ſuche a law, that is to ſay the law of Chriſt, that if we wyl with mekenes ſtudy howe we myght come to the true knowlege of it, we ſhall pleynly ſe in it the true concluſions of al thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be neceſſarye to our ſaluation. And if our priſtes wolde be loth to haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel knowen, it coude not be thought to be bicauſe the truth will not appere by it, for in dede as they knowe beſt, all truth apereth in it. And therfore if they ſhulde reſiſte to haue it come to perfite knowlege, it were lyke that they dydde it for feare that it ſhulde appere therby,
<pb facs="tcp:4934:33"/> howe far theyr maner of lyuyng nowe in theſe dayes varieth fro it, than that they ſhulde doubt that the trouth wold not appere by it: what then ſhuld moue vs to leue that trouthe, and tourne vs to the vncertayne chaunce of battaylle and warre? If we do ſo, we ſhewe our ſelfe by our dedes to folowe the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and ſaraſyns rather then our mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſte, though we wolde with our wordes happely ſay nay. And if ſuche a generall counſayle were gathered, it is no doubte, but that they wolde holly agree, that the clargie ſhoulde haue all the power and auctoritie that was gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to them of Chriſte. For they might not take it fro them if they wolde.</p>
               <p>And ouer that it is not to ſuppoſe, but that they wold agre alſo: that the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie ſhuld hold and enioy al ſuche aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie, libertie, &amp; power, as hath in tyme paſt ben graunted to them by temporal princis, or that they haue by cuſtome had poſſeſſion of, ſo that it ſtande with the honour of god, encrece of the faith,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:4934:33"/> and the tranquillitie of the people. And if they pretende to haue any auctoritee, that ſtandeth not therwith, it were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good for them ſelfe, ne for none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they ſhulde haue it any len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And ferther more there is yet one thynge, that dothe as moche hurte, as I trowe any other thinge dothe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>What is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>That there is an opinion amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge moche people, that ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny of the clergie, bothe ſpiritual rulers and other vnder them, haue taughte &amp; preched in tymes paſte diuers thinges, more ſpecially for their owne ſyngular profite and honour, then for the honour of god or welthe of the ſoules of the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp; that yet they endeuour them ſelfe no more to eaſe the myndes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple therin then they do. For neyther do they make it appere to the people, that they grudge therin without cauſe, and ſo offende god therby: ne yet refourme they not that that the people gruge at.</p>
               <p>And nowe if any man wyll ſaye, that good indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie wolde, that we ſhulde
<pb facs="tcp:4934:34"/> haue touched alſo defautes in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraltie more thenne we haue done, to that I wyll ſaye thus, that I am right farre deceyued, but this be true, that the worlde ſhall neuer come to a good peace and perfyte reformation, tyll the ſpiritualtie, eyther by their owne free wyll, or els by a good diligent callinge on of the temporaltie, be fyrſte refour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and that then they in charitie and in a pure loue to god and to the people, putte to their handes to reforme ſuche thynges, as they thynke to be myſuſed by temporall men, whiche yf they do, it is not to doubte, but that they ſhall righte ſhortely brynge the matter to a good effecte. For it is no lyttel thynge, that ſpirituall men maye doo therin, if they wyll, and if they wyll in no wyſe lay their handes to the matter, I think verily, that it wyll be harde to brynge the worlde to a good reformation: but that it ſhall abyde ſtyll out of order, as it hath done in tyme paſte.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:4934:34"/>
            <head>¶Who is the higher iudge in ſuche corrections, as be called ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual corrections, the kyng or the clergye. The ſeconde Chapytre.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>AL.</speaker>
               <p>If the partie in anye ſuite in the ſpiritual courte wyl appele, the order of his appeale is appoynted by the ſtatute made an .xxv. R. Hen. viii. and the ſtatute is, that if he appele fro the archebyſhoppe, that he ſhall appele to the kynges maieſtie in his chaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, and that vpon euery ſuche appele a commiſſion ſhall be directed to ſuche perſons, as the kynge ſhal name to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyne the cauſe without ferther ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pele. And ſyth the kynge may appoynt commiſſioners to determyne the cauſe, I holde it no great doubte, but that the kynge hym ſelfe is the hyghe iudge vppon euery ſuche appeale.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIZAN.</speaker>
               <p>yea but my meanynge is in ſuche ſuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, where there is none appele taken:
<pb facs="tcp:4934:35"/> but that the ſpirituall iuges gyue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ageynſt the partie, and appoynte him ꝑcaſe to do vnreaſonable penance, whether he maye haue any remedye by the lawe of the realme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>What thynkeſt thou in that queſtion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>That he hath no remedy by the kinges lawe. For if he obey not the ſentence, he ſhalbe accurſed. And if he ſtande accur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed .xl. dayes, the kynge, vpon the Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificat of the byſhop, is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of iuſtice to awarde a writte, that is called a writ <hi>de excommunicato capiendo,</hi> and thervppon ſhall he lye in priſon tyll he haue aswel ſatisfied the churche of the contempte, as of the wronge done to her. For the ſtatute of <hi>Circumſpecre agatis</hi> is, that cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rections, whiche p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lates make for deed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſynne, as for fornicacion, auoutrie, &amp; ſuche other: the ſpirituall iudge, if he procede to the correction of the ſynne, ſhall holde plee, not withſtandyng the kynges prohibition. And by the ſtatute of <hi>Sub qua forma,</hi> yf bodyly penaunce be enioyned, and the partie wyll freely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:4934:35"/> it for money, he may doo it. And ſo it ſemeth, that the corrections of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, auoutrie, and ſuche other, by the which terme (ſuche other) be vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtande vſerie, ſimony, yea and periury, and ſklaunder in ſome caſes, perteyne of very right to the prelates to correct. And though they aſſigne vnreaſonable penaunce, yet I ſuppoſe there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, but by appeale. And yf the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie leſe the adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage of his appele, then he hath put hym ſelfe without remedy. And ferthermore by the conſtitution ꝓ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynciall, that is in the thyrde boke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the conſtitutions, <hi>De immunitate eccleſie,</hi> which begynneth, <hi>Seculi principes,</hi> It appereth, that he that is in priſon, for that he is excommunicate, oughte not to be delyuered tyll he haue made ſatisfaction as well to the churche, as to the partie: And ſo ſythe the churche may aſſigne the ſatisfaction, it ſemeth that the churche is the high iudge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>I perceyue thy conceyt wel, but er that I anſwere the therin, I ſhall ſhewe the
<pb facs="tcp:4934:36"/> my conceyte in a nother thynge, that is to ſaye, that as I ſuppoſe, ſuche ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall corrections as nowe be vſed for fornication, auoutrie, and ſuche other be not merely grounded vpon the lawe of god, but by the law of man, &amp; in this realme they ben done by the clergy, by a cuſtome of the realme, except only the ꝓces of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication. And if the kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges courte had vſed to haue holden ple alſo of fornication, and auoutrie, and ſuch other the clergy could not of right haue compleyned of hit. And I holde it no great doubte, but that the parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment myghte yet ordeyne, that it ſhuld do ſo herafter. But parauenture it was thought at the begynnynge of that cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, that it was more eaſe for the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, and leſſe expences, and parauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more conueniente to haue ſuche ſmalle matters ſued in the ordinariis courte, then in the kynges courte: and therfore it was then ſo ſuffered to be. But if it ſhoulde happen to appere by experience, that it were as good or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:4934:36"/> to the kynges ſubiectes, to haue ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue matters determined in his courtes, as in the ordinaries: It ſhoulde ſeme good to brynge ſuche corrections to the kynges courte. For tho ſynnes may be corrected there, as wel as in the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all courte. For hit is here to be noted, that although a man be enioyned in the ſpirituall court to do ſuch compulſato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie penaunce as is there comonly vſed, and he doth it: yet he muſte after that be confeſſed of the ſame offence, &amp; take penaunce of his goſtely father. And ſo myght he do if he were fyrſt corrected in the kinges court. Neuertheles I ſpeke not this to thentent, that I wolde that ſuche ſuites ſhulde be broughte to the kynges courte, but that hit maye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, that prelates holde plee therof by the cuſtome of the realme, and by the ſufferaunce of the kynge and of his lawes: and not by the i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mediate aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the lawe of god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYSANCE.</speaker>
               <p>If they may holde plee of ſuche thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, it is all to one effecte, whether it be
<pb facs="tcp:4934:37"/> by the lawe of god, or by the lawe of man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>Nay for if they haue it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by cuſtome, it may with a cauſe be ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken fro theym, and that maye happely cauſe them to take the better hede, how they order theym ſelfe in hit. And yf it were by the lawe of god: then it might in no wyſe be altered.</p>
               <p>¶And as to the correction of hereſie, the kynge hath alwaye ſene it doone in this realme: excepte the tyme that the ſtatute that was made in the ſeconde yere of kyng Henry the .iiii. concerning hereſies, ſtode in effecte. For if a man before that ſtatute, had bene delyuered by the ordinaries to the laye courte for hereſye, he myght not haue bene putte in execution withoute a wrytte fro the kynge, but with a wrytte fro the kyng, after the olde cuſtome of the realme, he myghte then laufully haue bene put in execution. But yet as I take hit, the kyng was not then vpon euery requeſt made for ſuch a wryt, bounde forthwith to graunte it, but that he myghte take
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:4934:37"/> a reſpite to ſe the proces, &amp; thervpon to graunte the wrytte or not to graunt it, as he ſawe to ſtonde with iuſtyce: but as it ſemeth there were ſome that were not content, that the execution ſhulde be delayed in ſuche caſe tyll the kynges wrytte came, but that he ſo delyuered, ſhoulde forthwith be put in execution, and after the ſaid ſtatute of ſecundo of Henry the fourth was made, by what conueyance I can not fully telle, but it is not vnlyke, but that the clergy labou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red it, wherby it was enacted, that in ſuche caſe the party ſo deliuered, ſhulde be put in execution, no mencion made that any ſuche wrytte ſhulde be ſued for to the kyng: by whiche ſtatute the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſo delyuered were ſometyme put in execution without any ſuche wryt, and ſometyme labour was made not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge the ſayde ſtatute, to haue ſuche a wrytte to ſaue all thynges vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and that the kynge ſhoulde take no diſpleaſure. But that was not done for neceſſitie but of policie. For the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb facs="tcp:4934:38"/> was in the lawe ſufficient warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te withoute wrytte. Vnder this maner diuers haue ben put in execution for he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſie, whervpon haue ryſen great mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and grudges amonge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, whan ſomme haue affirmed, that dyuers ſo putte in execution for hereſy were no heritikes. Wherfore the ſayde ſtatute of Hen. the fourth was repelled by the ſtatute in the .xxv. yere of kynge Henry the .viii. as reaſon and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence wolde it ſhoulde: and thervpon it is ordeyned, that if he that is laufullye conuicte for heryſy, refuſe to abiure, or after abiuration fall in relaps, and be duly accuſed or preſented and conuicte, that then he ſhalbe commytted to the laye power to be burned. &amp;c. The kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges writte, <hi>De heretico comburendo</hi> fyrſte had and opteyned for the ſame. And ſo the olde lawe is therin reuyued. And as me ſemeth it appereth euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, that in that execution the kynge is iugge. For it can not be done without his writ, whiche neuertheles he is not alwaye
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:4934:38"/> bounde to graunte, when it is aſked: but as vpon the ſight of the proces and ſentence, he ſhall thinke the ſentence to ſtande with reaſon and conſcience. For the ſtatute is not, that the kynge ſhall graunte the writte, but that the partie ſhalbe burned, the kingis writ <hi>De here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tico comburendo</hi> fyrſte had and opteyned for the ſame.</p>
               <p>¶And therfore if the thinge that he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted for, be no hereſie, as it may be, in ſome caſes, after the clergie, bicauſe it is ageynſte the cannons, and yet be none in dede, bycauſe tho cannons be ageynſt the cuſtome of the realme, and that in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall thynges: then may the kynge denye the writte. And then as to that treatiſe, that thou ſpekeſt of, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Circumſpecte agatis,</hi> I littel regarde it. For many men ſay, it is no ſtatute, but that it hath been ſo named to be by the prelates: And ſo it is ſayde in the nyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene yere of kinge Edwarde the thyrde, that it was. And hit is the more lyke to be ſoo, bycauſe the ſame Treatyſe,
<pb facs="tcp:4934:39"/> in maner worde for worde is putte in a conſtitution prouincial, as a thyng ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the kynges aunſweres: and in all the ſtatute bokes, that go abrode among the lerners of the lawes of this realme, it appereth not, that that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe ſhoulde be taken oute of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges aunſweres, as to the reders wylle appere. Neuertheles if it can be found amonge the kynges recordes, that it is a ſtatute, I wylle take no exception to it, ne yet to <hi>Sub qua forma,</hi> nor <hi>Articuli cleri.</hi> For as me ſemeth it maketh no greatte matter to the queſtion, that we be in hande with nowe, that is to ſaye, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be hygher iuge in ſpiritual corec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions after the olde groundes of the lawe, the kynge or the clergye, whether they be ſtatutes or not. For if a man be excommunicate, and ſo continewe .xl. days, the cuſtome is, that he ſhal vpon the Certifycat of the byſhop made ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the kynge, be taken and put in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as thou haſt ſayd before. But then thou knoweſt well, that if the partye ſo
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:4934:39"/> beinge in priſone, make ſurmys to the kynge, that he hathe offered ſufficiente caucion or gage, to ſatisfie the churche and they wyll not receyue it: that then the kynge ſhal commaunde the biſhop, that he takynge an able caucyon ſhal ſe the partie deliuerd out of priſon: and if he obey not the writte, than the kynge may delyuer the partie oute of priſon. And ouer that (if he wyll) he maye, as men thinke, put the biſhop to aunſwere to the contempte. For diſobeyinge his wrytte, and then ſhall the matter be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in the kinges chauncerie, and there it ſhall comme in tryall, whether the gage were ſufficiente or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>But whether ſhall that ſufficiencye be eſtemed as thou thynkeſt, accordynge to the penance aſſigned by the byſhop, or accordynge to the offence?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>It maye be, that there is no penaunce yet geuen, or parauenture he is accurſed vppon a contempte for not apperance. But if the penance be gyuen, &amp; he wyll not do it, wherfore he is accurſed, and
<pb facs="tcp:4934:40"/> thervpon he is in priſon vpon the wryt <hi>De excommunicato capiendo,</hi> and thervpon he offereth a gage: I thynke that there the ſufficiencye of the gage ſhall be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, accordynge to the offence, for the penaunce maye be vnreaſonable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZAN.</speaker>
               <p>And yf the kynge take vppon hym to trye the greatnes or lyttelneſſe of the offence by his lawes, than he taketh vpon hym the keys of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>Naye, for that may be valued as welle by the kynges lawes, as it may by the byſſhop, yf the partye wyll redeme his penaunce for money. But if the kynge wold for the refuſing of his Caution take vpon him to make the abſolution hym ſelfe: then myghte hit be ſayde, he medled with the keyes. But ſythe he dothe no more, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelle the byſſhoppe to make abſolucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, accordynge to his lawes: It can not be ſayde, that he medleth with the keys.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BY.</speaker>
               <p>The proces of a contempte, that thou ſpekeſt of, hath not ben ſene. And ouer that the prelates compleyne,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:4934:40"/> that if the byſhop refuſe to take the cau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, that thenne an other wrytte ſhall go to the ſhyreffe to delyuer the partie out of priſone, as thou haſte ſayde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and in that wrytte they ſay, there is no mencyon made, that eyther the churche or the partie ſhall be ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And that is the princypalle cauſe, why the ſayde Conſtitution, <hi>Seculi prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes,</hi> was made:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>Thoughe the proces of a contempte hath not ben ſene in the ſame ſelfe caſe, yet the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a contempte hathe benne ſene in lyke caſes, for diſobeyinge the kynges wryttes, and that that is all vppon one lyke reaſon, ſhall be taken of one lyke lawe.</p>
               <p>And to that other point, that thou haſt moued, If the kynge vpon the refuſell of the gage delyuer the ꝑtie out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, without ſatisfienge the partie, or the chyrche eyther: I praye the ſhewe me thy mynde, what wronge hath the churche therby?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIS.</speaker>
               <p>It hath wronge for this cauſe. For the lawe of the
<pb facs="tcp:4934:41"/> churche is, that if a man be accurſed, he ſhall neuer be aſſoylled, but that he ſhall fyrſte make an othe, that he ſhall obey the commaundement of hym that ſhall aſſoyle hym, and that before he be aſſoyled he ſhall make amendis to the parties greued, if he be able, and if he be not able, than he ſhall make an othe, that he ſhall do it whan he is able. And by that wrytte, <hi>De caucione admittenda,</hi> he is delyuered out of priſon, and neyther the churche ne the partie ſatiſfied.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>And though he be ſo, yet neither of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath wronge. For he is yet accurſed as he was before, and may, er he be aſſoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, make ſuche othe as ſhall be reſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but that othe that thou haſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred before is clerely agaynſte the lawes of the realme. But yf the kynge in that caſe pretended, that when the partie were ſo delyuered out of pryſon, that he ſhulde alſo be diſcharged of the execution, then had the clergie ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to complaine, but nowe haue they none at all. And as to makyng amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:4934:41"/> to the partie, It ſtandeth not with the cuſtome of the realme, that the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie ſhulde haue power to make any a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes to the partie, but only that they in certayne caſes maye gyue penaunce for the ſynne. And therfore for beatyng of a clerke, the amendes for the treſpas ſhall be made in the kynges court: and for the layenge of violente handes on the clerke, amendes ſhall be made in the ſpiritual courte, but yet they may aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſigne no peine pecuniarie, onles the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie frely wyl redeme his bodily penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with money without compulſion. And therfore there is one thynge in the ſayd Treatiſe, called <hi>Circumſpecte agatis,</hi> that maketh me the more to doute, whether it be a ſtatute or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>What is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>It is recited there, that for fornication, auoutrie, and ſuche other, there is ſometyme aſſigned by prelates bodily peyne, and ſomtyme pecuniarie peyne, &amp; I knowe not one caſe, where prelates for correction of ſynne may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne pecuniarie peyne. And therfore I
<pb facs="tcp:4934:42"/> thynke verily, the parlyamente wolde neuer haue made that recytalle. And thus it appereth ſufficientely, that by that deliuerye out of priſon, after the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſinge of the ſaid caution, the clergie hath no cauſe to ſay, that the churche or partie haue any wronge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZAN.</speaker>
               <p>Welle admytte hit be therin, as thou ſayſte, yet it can nat be ſayde, but that the cuſtome of the realme is broken by it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>Why what calleſt thou the cuſtome of the realme in ſuch caſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIZAN.</speaker>
               <p>That the kynge ſhall kepe in pryſone ſuche as be excommunicate by the prelates, tyll they haue ſatisfied the churche as well of the contempt as of the wronge. And that the cuſtome is ſuche, it appereth pleinly by the ſayde writ <hi>De exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mun. cap.</hi> For by that writ the kyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth the ſhireffe to iuſtifie hym that is exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate by the body, tyll he haue ſatisfied the churche of the contempt &amp; wronge, as is ſaide before. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is deliuered without ſuche ſatiſfaction, the writ is not obſerued, ne
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:4934:42"/> yet the cuſtome of the realme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>The writte is as thou ſayſte, but that is put into the writ rather to put the partie in a fere, &amp; to enduce hym to ſubmyt him the rather to his ordinarie, than it is to ſhew the plainnes of the lawe, or of the cuſtome of the realme, and that appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by the ſaid writ de <hi>Caucione admitten.</hi> For by that writ the king noteth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhop, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if he refuſe to take a reſonable caucion of the ꝑtie, that he wyl in that caſe do y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to hym perteyneth to do. And ſo it appereth, that the kyng hath ſome other thing to do in the matter, then to kepe the partie ſtyl in priſon. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if the cuſtome were preciſely, that the kynge ſhulde kepe the partie in priſon, tyll he had ſatisfied the church, it were far vnreſonable. For it may be, that the ordinarie iudged hit for ſymonye, vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, or periurye, or ſuche other, that was none: ſhoulde the kynge then be bounde to kepe the partie ſtylle in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone, and to do penaunce, where he is not giltie, it ſemeth not reaſonable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:4934:43"/>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>If the kynge iudge, what is ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and vſury, and what not: dothe he not take vpon hym to iudge vppon thinges mere ſpiritual, and ſo confun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the keyes of the churche?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>Thou muſte always conſyder, that (as I haue ſayde before) the lettynge oute of priſone of one that is exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate, hurteth not the keys, for that he ſhalbe accurſed ſtyll, when he is out of priſon, as he was fyrſte: and all that the kyng dothe therin, is to ſee, whether he may with conſcience kepe the party any len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in priſon or not. And I trowe thou wylt agree, that yf the kynge be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed, that he thinketh in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that it is no ſymony or vſuri, that the partie lyeth fore, that he maye not with conſcience kepe hym any lenger in priſon. And I praye the, let me knowe what thou thynkeſt therin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily thou haſte brought me in doute of the matter, and therfore I praye the, ſhewe me, what is the veray lawe and cuſtome of the realme, concernynge a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:4934:43"/> man that is ſo in priſone vpon a writte <hi>de excommunicato capiendo,</hi> as the thinketh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>I take the cuſtome and the lawe of the realme to be this, that he ſhall not be delyuered out of priſone, oneles the ordinarye certifye the kynge, that the impriſoned hath ſatisfied the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, or elles that the partie offer a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente Caucion to ſatisfie the churche, and the ordinarie refuſeth hit: or elles that the kynge or his Chaunceler be ſo throughly enformed in the matter, that it appereth vnto them, that the partie maye not with iuſtice and conſcience be kepte any lenger in priſon: As if the ſentence were gyuen for a thynge mere temporall, or that ſo playne and ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient witneſſe be broughte in, that it moueth the kynge and his chaunceler, to beleue that the fyrſte wytneſſe were vntrue, or that the examinour entered the ſayinge of the wytneſſe otherwyſe then the witnes teſtified.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZ.</speaker>
               <p>And if there be ſuche witnes, yet their ſayeng ſhall not be beleued: ne the kynge may
<pb facs="tcp:4934:44"/> not put in trial agayn, that is ones tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after the order of the ſpiritual lawe:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>To auoyde the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ication I agre well he maye not put the fyrſte proufe in triall agayne, as thou ſayeſt, but to order the kynges conſcience, &amp; to know whether he maye ryghtwyſely kepe the partye any lenger in priſon or not, he maye well examyne the truthe of the matter. For truth ruleth in conſcience, what ſoo euer the order of the lawe be, and therfore if the appelle, in an appele of morder be founde gyltie, &amp; the iudge of his owne knowelege knewe that he is not gyltie, he may not gyue iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t agaynſte hym, but muſt rather reſygne his office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIS.</speaker>
               <p>I agree well there, but I put caſe, that the appelle in thy caſe be founde gyltie by falſe verdite, &amp; the iuge by examination of wytneſſe, and by confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame iury alſo come to perfyt knowlege, that the appelle is not gilty, he may neuer the les in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> caſe geue iugement, and is bounde to do it, for he toke the examination againſt the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:4934:44"/> order of the law, &amp; therfore he muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue that knowlege, bicauſe he is com to it of his owne wronge, &amp; ageinſt the order of the lawe, &amp; euen ſo it is in this caſe. The king ne yet his chanceler nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought not to haue newli exai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ed the mater, ſeing that it was ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly tried &amp; proued before in the ſpiritual court, &amp; therfore they muſt remoue &amp; put away the conſcience that they haue gotten by that vnlawfull examination, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that they doo not attempte ſoo farre ageynſte the lawe an other tyme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>Though the iudge in the ſayde caſe of appele dyd ageynſt the lawe, to examyn new witnes, yet it is not like to this caſe. For in that caſe of appele, the verdite is of recorde in the ſame court, and it is giuen by auctorite of the ſame lawe, that he ſitteth as iuge to iuge v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, &amp; it is alſo tried after the order of the ſame law: ſo that vpon that matter ther is no ferther trial, wherfore I agre wel that he ought not to haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther any newe examination, but in this caſe
<pb facs="tcp:4934:45"/> the ſentence is giuen in an other court, and after another lawe, than the chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellour is ſette to iudge vppon. For he is ſette to iudge after conſcience, and not only after the order of the lawe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall nor temporall but in fewe caſes, and alſo the proces of excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to puniſhe ſynne, and to mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne vertue, but what punyſſhement of ſynne, and mayntenaunce of vertue is it, if the kynge kepe hym that is no offender in pryſone? And therfore I thynke the kynge or his chauncellour may well take a newe examination in the matter, and do therafter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIS.</speaker>
               <p>I fele thy conceyte well, but yet ſurely yf ſuche examination be vſed, hit wyll be thoughte by many, that the ſpirituall iurisdiction is therby greatly confoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, and that the kynge and his lawes do littel in fauour of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>I ſe well thou ſtyckeſt ſoore to the matter, and therfore to eaſe thy mynd ſomwhat therin I wyl moue the of two thynges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIS.</speaker>
               <p>What be they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>One is this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:4934:45"/> if the cuſtome were, that whan the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate is in priſon, vppon the wrytte of <hi>Excommunicato capiendo,</hi> that he ſhoulde be kepte ſtyll in priſon, tylle he haue ſatisfied the churche, whether he be ryghtwiſely excommunicate or not, were this a lawefull cuſtome?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIS.</speaker>
               <p>I thynke naye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>And this pretence that thou ſtyckeſt ſo moche vpon, that there ſhoulde be no examination of the matter is of the ſame effect. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de is, if the parlyamente dyd put clerely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the wrytte of <hi>Excommunicato capiendo,</hi> and lefte the matter in ſuche caſe, that the ordinaries ſhulde iuſtifie al excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municates by the cenſures of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, in the beſte maner they coude with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any helpe of the kynge or of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes, ſhulde the parlyament therby do any wronge to the keys of the churche?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BY.</speaker>
               <p>I thynke nay, for the power of the clergie concernynge ſuche excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations ſhulde neuer the les ſtond ſtyll in her full ſtrength. But yet it ſhoulde breake a good laudable cuſtome of the
<pb facs="tcp:4934:46"/> realme that was fyrſt begon in fauour of the clerge, &amp; of the ſpiritual iurisdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>thou ſayſte euen truth, and my meanyng is not that I wolde haue that cuſtome broken, but that it ſhulde appere, that thoughe hit were broken, that yet no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had cauſe to complaine, as thoughe the lybertie of the churche were therby brokin, or the keis violate, wherfore me thinketh it more expedient for the clergie, to take this matter as it is, that is to ſaye, that the kynge and his lawes be as well contente to haue ſuche rebelles, as haue deſerued puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, &amp; yet wyl not obey the keys of the church, correctio, as they be: but yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kynge &amp; his lawes ſhoulde therfore in any caſe be compelled, whether they wolde or not, to puniſhe an Innocente, it is not reſonable: &amp; thus it ſhuld ſeme to be the more indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t way, &amp; more ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cordynge with iuſtice, that the mater be examined before the king, &amp; that if it ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pere thervpon, that the partie offended not, that he be deliuerid out of priſon, &amp;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:4934:46"/> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ordryng of the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication be thervpon lefte to the conſcience of the byſhop, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to charge the kinges conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence or his chauncellours eyther, with kepynge of hym in priſon. And then to that thou haſt ſaid before, that if ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munications be taken, that it wyl be thought by many, that the kyng &amp; his lawes do litel in fauour of the ſpiritual iurisdiction, I pray the be iuge therin thy ſelf, whether it be moch or litel, that the kyng doth, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he only vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificat of the biſhop taketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑtie &amp; ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him in priſon, &amp; there kepith him, til he either ſatisfieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, or els if he complaine, that he hath wronge, exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the mater, he being in priſon, how be it I think, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in ſuch caſe may if he ſe cauſe let the ꝑtie to bayl, ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> examination, though the ſhereffe by the reſon of the ſtatute of weſtm<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i. may not do it. And nowe to our firſt matter, If the kynge wolde iudge vppon Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and vſury, thynkeſt thou that he ſhulde offende the keys?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZANCE.</speaker>
               <pb facs="tcp:4934:47"/>
               <p>I thynke ſoo, for ſymonye and vſurye be prohibited by the lawe of god, and it belongeth to the clergi to declare, what is the lawe of god, and what not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>Though ſymonie and vſury be prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite by the law of god, yet that proueth not, that princis may not therfore hold ple therof, for takyng away of an other mannes goodes, and alſo periurye be prohibyte by the lawe of god, and yet princes holde plee therof, and thoughe Symonye and vſurye be prohibite by the lawe of god, yet it is not declared by the lawe of god, what is ſymonie, and vſery and what not. And it ſemeth, that princis takyng to them ſpirituall men, as theyr counſailours, maye doo that well ynough. And if it were orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that for ſymonye that the kynges courte ſhulde holde plee, I ſuppoſe it wolde doo moche good. For hit is not vnlyke, but that manye offende therin, and yet I here but of lyttell correction in that behalfe. And therfore thoughe the kynge iudged vppon ſymonie, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:4934:47"/> vſerye, I ſuppoſe he offended not the keyes, thoughe happely as the lawe of his realme is nowe, he ſhulde offende his lawes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BY.</speaker>
               <p>Well I wyl take a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpyte to be auyſed, er that I ſhewe the my full mynde, in this matter, and I praye the lette me now fele thy conceyt, yf a manne be accurſed, for that he wyl not obey a decre in a cauſe of matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and he is in priſone for it vpon the writte <hi>De excommunicato capiendo,</hi> and offe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth a ſufficient caucion, to obeye the churche, ſhall it be accepted?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>yea as welle in that caſe, as in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other caſe, and hit ſhall be valued after the ſubſtance of hym that is in priſon. And if he wyll yet when he is oute of priſon, diſobey the decree, and not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, wherby he forfaiteth his caucion, than he may vpon a new information, made to the kynge in his chancerie, be taken agayne by a newe writte, <hi>De ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicato capiendo</hi> fourmed ſpeciallye vpon the caſe, and be kepte in priſon tyl he obey the decree. And ſo he may be in
<pb facs="tcp:4934:48"/> all caſes, where he is delyuered vpon a caucion, and kepeth not his promiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZANCE.</speaker>
               <p>Well I am content in this matter, but I pray the, whether may the kynge in any caſe denye a writ of <hi>Excommunicato capiendo,</hi> whan it is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the certificat of the byſhoppe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyredde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SALEM.</speaker>
               <p>yea and that maye be proued thus. It apperethe in the regeſtre, that if the kynge at the certificat of the byſhop, haue awarded forth a writ <hi>de Excommunic. ca.</hi> &amp; after the kyng before the partie is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the partye appealed before the ſentence, or that a prohibition was delyuered, and not withſtandynge the iudge proceded, whervppon an atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chement is hangynge before the kyng, or elles it appereth, that the plee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth clerely to the kynges courte: in al theſe caſes the kynge ſhall graunte forthe a Superſedeas, commandynge that the partie ſhal not be arreſted, and thervpon it foloweth, that if no wrytte be forthe, it may be denied, whan it is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:4934:48"/> aſked, and that if the partie be areſted, before the Superſedeas came, that the kynge maye for the ſame cauſes dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hym oute of priſon vpon a ſpeciall wrytte <hi>de excommunicato deliberando.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BISANCE.</speaker>
               <p>There is no writte <hi>de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicato liberando,</hi> in the regeſtre, but where the byſhop certifieth the kynge, that the parti hath ſatiſfied the church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>All writtes that be grauntable by the law, can not be in the regeſtre, &amp; the ſpecyall matters proue, that he ought to be deliuered out of priſon for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time, and ſo a writte may be fourmed vppon the matter wel inough to delyuer hym: howe be it he ſhall remayne yet accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnder ſuch maner, as he dyd before, &amp; may be taken ageyne, if nede be, and that is in fauour of the ſpiritual iuris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. For I trow therin is no te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel lawe more fauorable to the ſpiritual iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lawes of this realme be, &amp; yet if ſuche fauour be haply bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſomtyme, a defaute is founde ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at by the clergie, as thoughe the holle
<pb facs="tcp:4934:49"/> liberte of the clergie were broken ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, where no lybertie is broken at all, &amp; euen vpon ſuche a poynte was the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution <hi>Seculi principes,</hi> made. For the conſtitution in the begynning reciteth, that whenne ſuche excommunicate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be vpon the ſygnification of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates accordynge to the cuſtome of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, taken and put in priſone, that then the prelates, bycauſe they refuſe to take a gage, wherby the partye offreth to ſtande to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundmentis of the churche, and to obey the lawe, be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to delyuer the partie oute of priſon, whiche as it is ſayde, there the prelates maye not nor ought not to do, as thei ſay, before due ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made, and thervppon the ſayde conſtytution ſayth farther, that ſoo lay men vſurpe the keyes of power and counnynge, to the confoundynge of the iugement of the church, where the truth is, the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath gyuen no iudgement, that the partye ſhalbe commytted to priſone, for it hath no power ſo to do, but onelye to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:4934:49"/> excommunicate the party for the ſinne, and thervppon the kyng accordyng to his lawes hath delyuered the party out of priſon, that he impriſoned him ſelfe: bycauſe the byſſhoppe hath refuſed a reſonable caucion. And yet it foloweth in the ſaid conſtitution: Wherfore we ordeyne, that the excommunicate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones ſo taken in our prouince, and ſo goinge out of priſone agaynſte the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and cuſtomes of the churche of Englande, ſhall be to theyr more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion ſhewed excommunicate with rin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynge of belles, and lyghtyng of can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delles. &amp;c. And ſo that, that in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge of the ſayde conſtitution is called the cuſtome of Englande, as it is in dede, and is the very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawe of the realme, that a perſone exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate ſhall be layde in pryſone by the kyng vpon the certificat of the byſhop, is after called the libertie and cuſtome of the churche of Englande: wherby the conſtitution meneth, that he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goth ſo out of priſone, for that the byſhoppe
<pb facs="tcp:4934:50"/> refuſeth his caucion: and they that let hym out alſo, breken the libertie of the clergie of Englande, and vſurpeth the keys of power and cunninge, where in dede neyther theyr libertie, ne keys be touched: but the cuſtome of the realme (wherby they clayme their libertie) is obſerued. And if they coud proue the cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtome of the realme, wherby they claim y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> libertie broken, yet they ought not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, as though their libertie were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For it is no more their libertie then it is the libertie of al the people of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. For al the people of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de make the churche of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; it hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth al the people, and not only the cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie, to haue any one laudable cuſtome of the realme broken. And yet the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of that conſtitution is that that going out of priſon hurteth the clergie only. And ſuche ſingularite hath done moche hurte, and wyll do, as longe as it contynueth.</p>
               <p>¶And farthermore the cauſe why the ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayth, that prelatis may
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:4934:50"/> not nor ought not deliuer the impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the kinges writte <hi>De cautione ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittenda,</hi> the writte is, that thoughe as the kynge is informed, the partie hath offered to the byſhop a ſufficient gage, that he ſhall obeye the commandement of the churche, after the fourme of the lawe, and that the biſhoppe refuſeth to take hit. &amp;c. The kynge by that terme Lawe, meneth the lawe of his realme: whiche is, that the partie excommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, ſhall make amendis to the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che for the ſynne onely, and no ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the partie. For that perteyneth to the kynges lawe. And the lawe of the churche is, that ſatisfaction ſhal be made alſo to the partie. And for mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce of that ſatisfaction to be had by auctoritie of the ſpirituall lawe, the ſayde Conſtitution was made to putte the partie in feare to goo out of priſone by the kynges writte.</p>
               <p>And all this riſeth vpon the variance of the lawes, wherby greatte grudges &amp; expenſes, yea and moche vnquietnes
<pb facs="tcp:4934:51"/> haue enſued, and wyl do as longe as it and other thynges lyke ſhall be ſuffred to contynue as they do nowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BY.</speaker>
               <p>All ſuche expences and vnquyetneſſes be well prouyded for, by reaſon of the ſaid appele, that may be made into the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges Chancerie. For it is not to thynke, but that the commiſſioners, that ſhalbe aſſigned by the kynge, wylle order the matier after iuſtice, and accordynge to the kynges lawes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>I truſte they wyll, but yet it is not the eaſe of euerye pore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that may haply be wrongfully handeled in the ſpirituall courte, to ſue forthe a commiſſion vnder the kynges broode ſeale. And therfore if the olde forme of the kynges lawe be obſerued therin, tbat is to ſaye, that if the partie that is accurſed and impriſoned wylle offer a reſonable caucion to the byſhop, to obey the churche, accordynge to the kynges lawes, and he refuſe it, that then the kynge, accordynge to the olde cuſtome, ſhall let hym out of priſon, tyl he can fynde the meanes to brynge the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:4934:51"/> byſhoppe to order hym, accordynge to the kynges law, &amp; that all the proces of that conſtitution, wherby the partie for his ſo goinge out of priſon ſhuld to his more confuſion be ſhewed to be accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ryngynge of belles, and lygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge of candelles, ſhuld for the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it be auoyded: I ſuppoſe veryly it wolde do moche good. And yet I pray the my frende Byſance, lette me knowe thy mynde in one thynge concernynge this mater.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BY.</speaker>
               <p>What is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>That if a man be accurſed, and he is contented to make amendes, &amp; to haue his abſolution, but the byſhoppe wyll not take any amendes of hym: or if he take amendes, or put hym to penance, whiche he fulfylleth, yet he wyll not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyle hym, ne he wylle not certifye the kynge, that he is accurſed, ſoo that he myghte by helpe of the kynges lawes be diſmyſſed: but wylle ſuffre hym to ſtonde ſtyll ſo accurſed: what remedy hath the partie, as thou thynkeſt, to be diſcharged of that excommunication?
<pb facs="tcp:4934:52"/> And lyke wyſe if a man be accurſed for a thynge mere temporall, and wolde be diſcharged of it, and the byſſhoppe wil not diſcharge hym, what remedye hath the party to be aſſoyled?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZANCE.</speaker>
               <p>In thy laſte caſe the partye maye haue a Premunire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>And thoughe he take it &amp; recouer therby, yet he ſtandeth ſtyll accurſed. And alſo the partye and iudge may be deed, and then the premu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nire is gone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIS.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I thynke in bothe thy caſes, that if the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente be certified in to any of the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges courtes of recorde, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the king vpon the compleynte of the party may commaunde the byſhop to aſſoyle him, if he wyl order him ſelf according to the lawes of the realme, &amp; if he wyll not, he ſhal ren in a conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt againſt the kinge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>And if the byſhop wil not certifie the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in to none of the kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges courtes, ne vnto the kyng neither: what remedy hath the partie then, muſt he ſtonde alway accurſed, and be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite from heryng of dyuyne ſeruice, &amp;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:4934:52"/> fro all company of feythfull people du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge his lyfe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIZAN.</speaker>
               <p>It is not to be thought that any biſhop wyl deny abſolution, where he ought to make it: &amp; if he do, I pray the let me here thy con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyte, what remedy as thou thynkeſte, ſhulde lye in the caſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>Whether any biſhop wil do ſo or not I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not tel, but ſurely there is a great opinion amonge the people, that as the worlde hathe gone in tyme paſte, if ſuche an excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication had touched the power of a biſhop, or the libertie of the churche, or els that any greate man of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, had borne diſpleſure to the party, that he ſhuld haue right moch buſines, and alſo pay well for it, ere he ſhoulde haue his abſolution. But howe ſo euer it hath ben in tyme paſt, I beſeche oure lorde that the matter maye be ſoo well loked to, that hit be not ſoo here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, ne that vnreſonable penaunce, ne vnreaſonable money, for redeming of hit, nor for the coſtes of the ſuite, be not gyuen nor taken hereafter.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4934:53"/>
               <p>And as for a remedy for the partie to be aſſoyled, I thinke verily, that the king vpon the ſurmyſe of the partye, maye aswell co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande the ordinarie to make abſolution, ſo the partie order hym ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to the lawes, where the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mengement is not certified of recorde, as where it is. For me thynkethe, that the reaſon is all one in both caſes. For aswel ſhall he be prohibited fro diuyne ſeruice and communion in the one caſe as in the other. And if he haue any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſewe and take it, the ordinarye myght els diſable hym when he wolde. And lykewyſe if the byſhoppe aſſoylle hym, and when he hath ſoo done, wyll not make hym his letters of abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the kynge maye alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde hym to do hit, as me ſemeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIZ.</speaker>
               <p>There is no writte in the Regeſtre, that the king may write to the ordinarie to make ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolucion, where the exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication is not certified of record into the kynges courte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>And if there be not, it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth lytell. For if there be a lyke reaſon
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:4934:53"/> in an other caſe, as there is in that: the clerkes of the Chauncerie maye agree vpon a wryt. And yf the kynge myght not do, as I haue ſayd, it might happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that many of his ſubiectes ſhulde fayle of Iuſtice, and that the kynge coulde not helpe it. And therfore if the byſhop wyll not obey the kynges wrytte, an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachement ſhall go agaynſt hym to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the contempt: And then ſhall the mattier be determined after the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the kynges lawes. And ſo it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth (as me ſemeth) that euen after the olde lawe &amp; cuſtome of the realme, the kinge is the high and ſupreme iuge in ſuche corrections, though the ſayde ſtatute of .xxv. H. viii. had neuer bene made: and that he may ſee his ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis haue iuſtice in that behalfe, if they wyll calle for helpe vnto hym. But yf the partie in ſuche caſe, wyll ſubmytte hym ſelfe vnto the ordinary, then by the parties aſſent, the ordinarie may make the fynall concluſion: ſo he offende not the kynges lawes in his doinge.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:4934:54"/>
            <head>¶Of dyuers thynges concernynge ſaint Thomas of Canturbury. The .iii. Chapiter.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>AL.</speaker>
               <p>I knowe no man that ſayth, but that ſaynt Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas of Caunturbury is a bleſſed ſaynt in heuen: but parauenture there be ſome, that doute, what were the very articles, whervpon kyng Henry the ſecond, and he varied. And happely ſome wyl ſay, that he dyd more ageinſt the kynges prerogatiue, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ought to haue done, but though he dyd ſo in dede, yet that moueth me but lytel to thinke, but that he was and is a holy man, and a bleſſed ſaynt. For if he thought in his conſcience, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſenes and truthe bounde hym to do that he dyd, as I ſuppoſe verily it dyd, it ſuffiſed to hym. For ignorance may excuſe, but onely agaynſte the lawe of god, &amp; the lawe of reſon. And the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that the kyng and he varied vpon: were vpon the cuſtomes of the realme,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:4934:54"/> and the kynges prerogatyue: whiche ſainct Thomas thought, was ageinſte the libertie of the churche, wherin ſaint Thomas myght lightly be deceiued by ignorance: howe be it I thinke verily, that there is one thing, that derogateth and diminiſheth greatly the very true honour, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wold be giuen by many men to ſaint Thomas, if that were not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BY.</speaker>
               <p>What is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>It is that ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes exalt ſaint Thomas ſo high aboue other ſayntes, &amp; procure honour to him more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly is done to any of the apoſtels, and yet ſecretely ſtele the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to them ſelfe, and thinke them ſelf the more worthy honour for his dedes: and that hath cauſed ſome laye menne to haue leſſe deuocion to hym thanne they wolde haue hadde. And thoughe they do not wel in that doyng: yet it is good to al priſtes to loke vpon the mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. And ſomwhat to eaſe the myndes of the peple therin. And now wyl I ſay ſomwhat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward honour done to ſayncte Thomas before other
<pb facs="tcp:4934:55"/> ſayntes, that I coulde neuer ſee cauſe reaſonable, why all the commemorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the prouynce of Caunturburye ſhulde be ſaide more in his name, then in the name of ſaynt Auguſtyne the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtell of Englande, whiche broughte the fayth fyrſte in to this realme. For as farre as to manne appereth, ſayncte Thomas had neuer knowen the chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayth, ne had ben the holy doctryne of ſaynte Auguſtyne goinge before. And ſythe he was archebyſhoppe of Caun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbury as wel as ſaint Thomas was, &amp; the fyrſt and chiefe of al other archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops there: I can not ſe why the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorations ſhuld not be attribute to hym rather thenne to the other. And I thinke verily, that if it were ſo ordered to be, that a right greatte occaſyon of mekenes in many ſpiritual men ſhulde folowe thervpon: and it is no doubte, but that ſaynct Thomas wolde be alſo ryght highly pleſed therwith. And fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore I can not ſe any conueniency why ſaynte Thomas ſhoulde haue his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:4934:55"/> feaſt of his translation kept in ſo high ſolempnitie as it is accuſtomed to be: before other ſaynctis. And parauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that poynte with ſuche other lyke, Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gerſon mente to treate of in his treatiſe that he calleth in latine <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio defectuum uirorum eccleſiaſticorum,</hi> where he aduertſeth rulers to loke, whether it be conuenient, that ſome new ſaintis ſhuld haue more ſolemnitie in the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of god, then the auncient ſaynctes haue. And yet if the ſolemnitie to ſome of the apoſtols and to ſaynct Thomas be compared to gether, they be ryghte farre a ſonder. And therfore why his Tranſlation ſhulde be kepte holy day, and not the veray day of the depoſition of ſaynt Auguſtine, or of ſaynt Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, that was the fyrſte kinge of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, that was conuerted: or why the depoſition of ſaint Edwarde kyng and confeſſour, whiche fallethe in the .xii. days, as the depoſition of ſainct Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas dothe, ſhoulde not be had in more honour then it is, and ſainct Thomas
<pb facs="tcp:4934:56"/> to haue ſo moche, I can nat telle what the very conſideration ſhulde be of it. And verily I ſuppoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if the depoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſaynte Ethelbert, and of ſaynt Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and the translation of ſaynte Thomas were on the depoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſaint Auguſtyne kepte holy daye to gether, and the holy daye of the tranſlation of ſaynt Thomas to ceaſſe, and that prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes onely ſhoulde ſaye the ſeruyce of ſaynt Thomas on the day of his tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, &amp; the people not to be bound to here it, that it wold right highly pleſe ſaint Thomas, and cauſe many ꝑſons alſo to haue hym more in honour then they haue nowe. And here (as me ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth) it is ſomewhat to be meruayled alſo, that al we englyſhemen, as to the multitude of vs, canne report more of ſaint Denis of France, of ſaint Dauid of wales, ſaint Patrike of Irelande, &amp; of ſaint Ninian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called ſainte Tronion of Scotland, than we can of ſaint Auguſtine the apoſtle of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt brought the faith in to Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:4934:56"/> &amp; yet though as me ſemeth it were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaint Auguſt. were more honorid then he is, neuertheles I mene not ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, that ſeint Thomas ſhuld haue ani les true honor then he hath, but rather more. Ferthermore bicauſe there be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers articles put in bokes, which, as it is ſaid, ſaint Tho. ſhuld holde, I haue intitled herafter ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as I haue found the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> writen in a right ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t boke, &amp; ſhal ſhew my conceit, how the lawe of this realme, &amp; they agre together. But I wyl not expreſly affirme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaint Tho. held the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dede. For I neuer ſaw them as of a full auctoritie, nor I wote not where to find the ful auctorite of them: howbeit if his articles were pleinli &amp; bi ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t auctorite knowen, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhuld not be laufull for no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to adde no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ne to diminiſh any thing fro the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it were wel done. For as they ſtond now in an vncertaintie, many perſons take vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reporte many articles of hym, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as I ſuppoſe, he neuer helde: &amp; one of his articles, as I haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it<pb facs="tcp:4934:57"/> written in the ſayd boke is this. If con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trouerſie be vpon the preſentment of a benefice betwene lay me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and clerkes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge pretended that it ought to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyned in his courte: And it is ſaid, that ſaincte Thomas ſhulde fynde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault at this article, as a thyng ageinſt the libertie of the church. And ſurely it is not ageynſt the liberte of the church but is an olde laudable cuſtome of the realme, the kynges prerogatyue, and the right of his corowne. And if ſainct Thomas reſiſted it, he reſiſted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth. Howe be it that prouethe not, but that he is yet neuer the les a right holy and bleſſed ſainct, as I haue ſaid before.</p>
               <p>¶An other article is, that churches of the kinges gyfte may neuer be laufully gyuen without his aſſent. And this is alſo an olde prerogatiue to the kynge &amp; his progenitours, and is as moch to ſaye, as that in benefices, that be of the kynges gyft, no time ne laches renneth to the kinge, but that the kinge ſhal as well preſent after the .vi. monethes as
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:4934:57"/> before. And yf ſainct Thomas reſiſted that, he reſyſted the righte. For it is a laufull cuſtome, and a lauful preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue. For why the kynge ne none other patron within this realme claime none other right in ſuche preſentmentes, but after euery auoydance to preſent theyr clerke to the ordynarie. And yf he be able, than the ordinarie to receiue him: or els vppon a notice in ſome caſe, and in ſome caſe without notice, the patron at his peryll to preſent an other. And if the kynge preſent not, the ordinarie, tyl he preſent, may with the profites ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, appoynt one to ſerue the cure. But yf the kynge claymed alſo to haue the profytes of the benefice in the meane tyme, and he to ſe the cure ſerued hym ſelfe, tyll he preſented, that were more doubte.</p>
               <p>¶An nother article is this, that they that be accurſed ſhall not fynd pledges to reſtore, nor be ſworne to it: but only to fynde pleges to ſtande to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the church for their abſolution.
<pb facs="tcp:4934:58"/> And this article is alſo holden for lawe in this realme to this daye. For in caſe that the iuge ſpirituall wyl not aſſoyle the parti without reſtitution, where by the lawes of the realme he ought to do it: the kynge may vppon a contempte commaunde hym to doo it. And if he wyll nedely procede to compell reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a prohibition lyth. And that is the very cauſe why an exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mengement cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified before the kynges iuſtice by the pope, was neuer alowed in this realm, bycauſe the kynge myght not write to Rome to make the abſolution, in caſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by his lawes the ꝑtie ought to haue it.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo an nother article is, that the churche ſhall not defende goodes that be forfayte.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo that plees of det belonge to the kingis court, though an othe be made.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo that the ſonne of a bonde man ſhal not be made preſt without lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the lorde. Theſe three laſte articles be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for law in this realm to this day. And yet it is ſaide, that ſaint Thomas
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:4934:58"/> reſiſted theym.</p>
               <p>¶And as to the thyrde artycle of the ſaid thre laſte articles, the lawe is this, as I take it, that if the ſonne of a bond man be made prieſt without the lordes licence, that yet he is a bondman as he was before, and the lorde may compell him to do him ſeruice, as to a prieſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth, before any other. And though the truth were that ſaint Thomas reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted theſe articles al that he coulde, and that he is yet neuertheles canoniſed as a ſaint, that proueth nothyng thoſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles to be vnlaufull. For yf he in his conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thought them vnlaufull, that ſuffiſeth to hym, as I haue ſaid before.</p>
               <p>¶And more ouer if all the clergie of chriſtendome wolde prohibite the ſaide articles, or any article of the law of this realme, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is not againſt the law of god nor the law of reſon: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prohibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld not be of effect in this realme. And ther be dyuers other artycles in bokes &amp; le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendis, wherin he reſiſted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of the realme without cauſe, if it be as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide
<pb facs="tcp:4934:59"/> bokes doo teſtifie, whiche I remytte to the iudgement of theym that wyll take the peyne to rede them. And ouer that in the bokes of ſome pardoners, that haue gone about for ſaynt Thomas, be conteyned many and dyuers friuolous and vntrue thynges for procurynge of money: as it is of this article, that ne had ſaynt Thomas ben, no man ſhuld haue ſette his chylde to ſcole, nor haue eaten in his houſe, pygge, goſe, nor ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, but he ſhulde haue payed a fyne to the kynge. And dyuers other thynges be thus imagyned, wherby the people be greattely illuded and deceyued, and ſaynt Thomas right highly diſpleſed. For he loueth no vntruth, and yet they haue bene ſuffered to paſſe ouer frome yere to yere without correction: doſte thou not thynke my frende Byſaunce, that ſuche thynges wolde be reformed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BYZAN.</speaker>
               <p>Forſoth I thinke it right ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, that rulers and gouernours loke well vpon ſuche matters. But yet ſomme men wyll parauenture thynke,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:4934:59"/> that it is not conuenient, for lay men to ſpeake of ſuche highe thynges, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to great clerkes and hygh lerned men. And I haue harde ſome men ſay my ſelfe, that before laye men ſpake of ſuche high matters, the worlde was in good peace and quietnes, and that ſith they medled therwith, the worlde was neuer well, but ful of trouble, diuiſion, and ſtryfe. And therfore it wyll pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture be better for the and me, to let theſe matters paſſe, tyll our lorde ſhall put the rulers in mynde to loke vpon them, and ſe theim refourmed, then to ſpeke any more of them, and lyttyll ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte or none to folowe of our ſpekyng.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>The more that the rulers here of the gruges that be amonge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the more wyll they regarde theym, and wyll the rather ſette to theyr aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce to helpe to auoyde them, ſythe they be as well to the high diſpleaſure of almighty god, as to the great hurte of the common welth of all the people. And I thynke verilye, that a common
<pb facs="tcp:4934:60"/> welth ſhal neuer ryſe, as longe as theſe gruges continue. And therfore I truſt our ſpekyng ſhal not be clerely in vain, ſithe ſome cauſis of the ſaid grudges &amp; diuiſions may happly be put in mynde therby, whiche elles ſhoulde not haue ben remembrid. And ther be many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidentes, by the which it appereth, that laye menne haue reaſonned in ryghte hight matters. Fyrſte when the ſtatute of .xxv. of Edward the third, that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>De aduocationibus,</hi> was made, was it not (as thou ſuppoſeſt) argued &amp; reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whether the parliament might ſet remedy in ſuche caſes, where the pope made collatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or reſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to any be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nefices within this realm? And who re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoned that matter, as thou thinkeſt, but the lordes temporal &amp; the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons? veri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly none. For the lordes ſpirituall durſt not therin reſiſt the pope. And no more they durſt when the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was aſked in the parlyament, Anno .xvi. Rich. ii. whether the pope myghte translate a byſhop in this realme without the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:4934:60"/> aſſent, whervnto the biſhops made a proteſtation, that it was not theyr in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente to ſaye, but that the pope myghte make ſuche tranſlacions by the lawes of the churche: but they ſayde it was agaynſt the kyng and his crowne, if he dyd it. And the comons ſayd, that they wolde ſticke with the kinges right in it vnto the deth. And the lordes temporal ſaide, that they wolde be with him with al their power. And it ts not to thynke, that theſe aunſweres were made ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly without great reaſonyng before. And who ſhoulde reaſone hit, but the lordes temporalle and the commons, and ſpecially they that were lerned in the lawes of the realme.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo ſithe it is recyted in the writ <hi>De excommunicato deliberando,</hi> that the king at the peticion of the biſhop co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the ſhyreff to iuſtifie ſuche a certein perſon by his body, as a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pning the keis of the church, til he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied the church. &amp;c. with diuers other thynges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly vſed to be put into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4934:61"/> ſayde writte, whiche be here omytted: are not they then that be lerned in the lawes of the realme, ſpecially they that ſhall be of the kynges counſell, bounde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to aduertiſe the king, what is a contem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge of the keyes of the churche, and what not: ſo that he ſhulde not in ſuch caſe do any thynge agaynſt the keys of the churche? I trowe no man wyl ſay, but they be. For els the kynge ſhulde happely be enforced to gyue credence to ſpiritual men in maters concernyng their iurisdiction ageynſt his owne. It is not therfore conuenient for any man to ſay, that lay men ought not to reſon the power of the churche. For if it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myniſhe the right of the crowne, waſte the ſubſtaunce of the realme, prohibite the laboure or lyuynge of the people, they may well ſpeake of it. And alſo ar bounde to ſpeake of it, ſpecially they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be lerned in the lawes of the realme.</p>
               <p>¶And where thou ſayſte, that before that laye men ſpake of ſuche matters, the worlde was in good peaſe and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes:
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:4934:61"/> ſurelye if the people grudged, and durſte not ſpeake, ne wyſte not to whome to ſpeake or complayne: then was that peace that thou ſpeakeſte of, lyke to the peace that the prophet Iſaie remembreth in his .xxi. chapter, where he ſayeth, <hi>In pace amaritudo mea amariſsima,</hi> That is to ſaye, In peace is my moſte bitternes. For when the people wolde haue ſpoken, and durſte not, that was greate grefe to them. And then if they be at lengthe enforced to ſpeake, and trouble and ſtrife riſe by their ſpeking: it is not longe of their ſpeakynge, but of them that gyue them occaſion ſo to murmour and grudge, and that wylle meyntein forth the old abuſions, &amp; not ſuffre them to be reformed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BI.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſte recyted many thinges in theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions, that thou thynkeſte wolde be refourmed, and in ſome poyntes thou haſt deuiſed howe they may be refour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but thou haſte not done ſo in all: I pray the therfore let me here thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte by what meanes (as the thinketh)
<pb facs="tcp:4934:62"/> ſuche thinges as thou haſt not yet tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the reformation of, might be refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>To trete fully of the remedies of ſuch abuſions, perteyneth moſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially vnto the rulers: howe be it one thyng encorageth me very moche to do that in me is to ſay ſomwhat in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BI.</speaker>
               <p>What is that that encorageth the to it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>That ſhal I ſhewe the fyrſte with good wyll, and after I ſhal touche ſhortely ſomme of the remedies, and ſhall commyt the reſidue to them, that it moſte ſpecially perteyneth to, to loke vpon it.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶Of certayne thinges, that ſhoulde ſeme to be occaſions to brynge good peace and quietnes betwixt the clergie and the people. The .iiii. Chapitre.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>ALEM.</speaker>
               <p>Fyrſte the thyng, that encouragethe me to ſpeake of a refourmacyon betwyxt the clergie and the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:4934:62"/> laye people, is for that as me ſemethe, if the matter be well and throughly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon, there is not ſo great varia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ne diuerſities of opinions betwixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ne betwixte the clerkes and great ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, that ſeme to take parte erneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the matter on bothe partes, as is reported to be, ſpecially in the matters that be moſte of ſubſtaunce: and that may appere thus. The clergie preache and teache, that our lorde Ieſu Chriſt, very god and man, is the very ſauiour of the worlde, redemyng vs by his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And the other do euen lyke wiſe, and take hym as the verye Medya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour betwixt god and man, and none but hym.</p>
               <p>¶The clergie alſo teche, and preche, that al men be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to beleue ſcripture, that is to ſay, the olde teſtament &amp; the newe, and to folowe it as a thyng moſt neceſſary to our ſaluation. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other be euen of the ſame opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that is betwixt them therin ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth ſpecially in this poynte: The clergie
<pb facs="tcp:4934:63"/> pretende, that they onely ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ſcripture to the laye menne, and that they oughte to folowe theyr tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge and declaration therin, and not to expounde it them ſelfe, ne to haue it in theyr mother tongue: And manye laye men, and alſo ſome great clerkes holde the contrarie, and ſaye, that it is laufull, and alſo neceſſarie for lay men to haue ſcripture in the mother tonge, to the intente, that whenne they haue none to preche it to them, that they that can rede the mother tong, as many can whiche vnderſtande no latin, may rede it to their own conſolation and inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to the inſtruction of other alſo. ¶They varie alſo ſommetyme of the vnderſtandynge of ſcripture, and howe it ſhall be taken: but that is moſte ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in ſuch poyntes, as concerne the worldely honour, power, or rycheſſe of the clergye, as hit is of this queſtyon: whether it be laufull to the ſucceſſours of the apoſtels and diſciples of Chriſt, to haue poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: but in thinges mere
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:4934:63"/> ſpirituall concernynge ſcripture, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly they do not varie.</p>
               <p>¶And lykewyſe there is no ſuche dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſite of opinions, as ſome men haue taken hit to be, betwyxte Feythe and good warkes. For bothe parties agree, that good warkes be neceſſarye vnto ſaluation: and the thynge that ſemeth to be as a variance betwixt them therin is onely vpon termes, and not in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as thus: The one parte ſayth, that feyth without good warkes is but a deed feyth, and profiteth not to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And after as they meane, they ſaye trouth. For they meane of a naked feyth of a man, that hath neyther cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite nor good warkes: but that he hath feythe, and lyeth in deedly ſynne, and dyeth without repentance. In whiche caſe the feythe ſuffiſeth not to hym, as they affirme it doth not: but they deny not, but that if ſuche a man in the later ende come to repentance, though it be euyn atte the laſte poynte, but that he ſhal be ſaued, and that that repentance
<pb facs="tcp:4934:64"/> ſhalbe acceptable for hym afore god in place of the good warkes that he had not, and that his rewarde ſhalbe after the mocheneſſe or littelneſſe of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition and ſorowe. And the other parte ſaythe, that feythe onely iuſtifieth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god: and they alſo, after as they meane, ſaye trewely. For they calle hit no feyth, onleſſe it haue good warkes. And therfore they ſtyrre the people to good warkes all that they canne, that they maye haue a lyuely feythe: for they ſaye, that yf a man beleue all the articles of the feythe, and all that he is commaunded to beleue beſide, and lyueth in deedly ſynne, that he hath no feythe. And ſoo it appereth, that theſe menne varye not in effecte in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, but in termes: howe be it a littell variance there is betwixt them therin, vnder this maner: They that ſay, that feith iuſtifieth before god, wene y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many people haue ſuch a truſte in theyr good warkes, that they hope to be ſauid only by theym. And ſurely if any be of that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:4934:64"/> opinion, they be far deceyed. For none ſhalbe ſaued but through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and goodneſſe of oure lorde. And therfore to gyue the people occaſion, that they ſhal truſte in grace more then in theyr good warkes, they extolle feith and grace aboue good warkes. And the other partie ſaythe, that there is none that truſteth onely in his good warkes. And therfore they ſaye, that it nedeth not to extolle faythe ſo moche as they do. But nowe admytte it be as they ſaye: yet me ſemethe, that yf any manne doubte, whether they doo ſoo or not, and therfore he inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctethe theym, that they oughte not to do ſoo, that hit is a good dede, and oughte charytablye to be accepted of all menne, and that they oughte not to be reproued for it.</p>
               <p>¶Then ferther more manye haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, that there be ſomme menne of opinion, that all thynges ought to be in common, ſo that if oone lacked, he myght take it of his neighbour.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4934:65"/>
               <p>¶And of all other opinions, that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion go the moſte nigheſt to the diſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the common welthe. For it is a maynteyner of ſlouthe and idelnes, and a deſtroyer of all good labour.</p>
               <p>And there be many other that ſey, that there be none of that opinion: but they ſey, that they haue harde many of this opinion, that in tyme of neceſſite of our neighbour, all thynges that we haue, oughte to be in common to hym, and we be then bounde in charite to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of our goodes vnto hym, after as his neceſſitie requyreth: but that any might take it them ſelfe, they ſay, they haue harde none of that opinion. And ſurely I thynke it is true as they ſay. And ſaint Auguſtin to that effect ſaith thus: He that ſeeth his brother in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſite, and ſhytteth his helpe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte from hym: howe abydeth the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of god in hym? And I beſeche our lorde ſende vs many of that opinion, that is to ſay, that we ought to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate of our goodes to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:4934:65"/> that be in neceſſitie: and not to ſende vs ſo moche as one of the other opinion, that is to ſay, that they might take it them ſelfe. And that if there be none of that opinion, that then there be none, that wyll report there is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BY.</speaker>
               <p>I perceyue wel, that thou thinkeſt, that there be not ſo great diuerſities of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions amonge the people, as are noted to be, if the very trewe intent of theyr myndes were throughly knowen: how be it ſomme cauſes of grudges thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeſt that there are yet remaynynge. And therfore though the remedies ther of perteyne moſt ſpecially to the rulers to trete vpon: yet as it ſemeth, it can do no hurt, if thou ſhewe thy mynde ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what therin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SAL.</speaker>
               <p>Somewhat in a generalitie I wyll ſay with good wyll. And fyrſt I thynke that it is right ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, that the lawes and iurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſpiritual and temporal be through<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly agreed to gether: for vpon the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge of them this inconuenience folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth: that whan ſome occaſion of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance
<pb facs="tcp:4934:66"/> happeneth to ryſe betwixte two men, and they aſke counſayle, one at the ſpirituall lawe, and the other at the temporal lawe, that bothe be informed that they haue right, and that cauſeth theym to ſtycke ſo ſoore to theyr titles, that they be farre fro any meane way, where if eyther of theym were inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the lawe were ageynſte hym, as moſte commonly the one of theym ſhoulde be, if they bothe aſked coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle at one lawe: that wold cauſe him that thought the lawe agaynſt hym, to eſchewe expences, and falle to agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo it is ryght expediente, that all conſtitutions prouincialle and legan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, as haue ben made in tyme paſte, ageynſte the lawes of the realme, and the kynges prerogatiue, where the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of the realme oughte of righte to be folowed: and alſo all ſuche lawes as be ouer greuous to the people by ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tendynge ouer great multitude of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications vpon theym: or that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:4934:66"/> haue bene made more of ſingularitie, and in mayntenaunce of the ſpirituall iurisdiction then of charitie, ſhall be clerely reuoked and put away.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo it ſemeth expedient, that none hereafter haue but onely one benefice with cure, by lycence nor otherwyſe, and he to be reſident vppon it, excepte ſuche as haue moo nowe at this tyme, and they to inioye theym, withoute ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng any mo by permutation or other wiſe. And if any take mo benefices the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one, bothe to be voyde.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo it ſemeth to ſtande with chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that lyke as there is appoynted cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne collettis and oriſons for infidels in lent, that there be a ſpeciall collette for them all tymes of the yere bothe at mattens, maſſe, euynſonge, complin, Placebo and dirige: and lykewyſe for the peace and tranquillitie of all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten realmes, ſpeciallye nowe in this daungerouſe tyme.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo that all parkes and paſtures, that be in the handes of ſpiritual men,
<pb facs="tcp:4934:67"/> and be mete for tyllage, be by a certain tyme buylded and tourned into tyllage vpon a peyne. &amp;c. And for as moche as moche tymbre wyll be ſpent aboute it, and tymbre is greatly waſted in many places, that it be diuiſed, howe tymbre and wodde maye be increaſed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued hereafter. And me thinketh ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge the kynges grace and his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle haue diuiſed ſo good a waye for nouryſhynge of wodde in Irelande, as they haue done, that it were very well, that if they did likewiſe for this realm. ¶Alſo it ſemeth to be right expedient, that certayne articles, whereof parte ſhall be recited hereafter, be gathered to gether, and that preachers be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, that in euerye ſermon, they ſhall moue the people to fulfylle them, as nygh as god ſhall gyue them grace: and ſuche other alſo as the parlyament ſhall thynke conuenient. And not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyte euery article in euerye ſermon, for it wolde ſomtyme be tedious, but part of theym, as they ſhall thynke mooſte
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:4934:67"/> profytable for the audience. And one of the ſaid articles, as it ſemeth, may be this, that the preacher diligentlye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe the people, what warkes beſte pleaſe god: and alſo to inſtructe them, in what order they ought to be done.</p>
               <p>And for a remembrance I ſhall brefely touche ſomewhat of that mattier, and commytte the ferther declaration ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the preachers.</p>
               <p>¶The worke that moſte pleaſeth our lorde, as I take for the laie people, is the releuynge and comfortynge of our neighboure, that hathe nede: and the greatter that his nede is, the greatter ſhall be our rewarde. And as prayer &amp; contemplation be the higheſt warkyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in the lyfe contemplatife: ſo is this dede of mercy to our neighbour, done in charite, the higheſt warke in the lyfe actiue. And therfore no man can come vnto it, but by great labour and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. For it is alway harde to atteyne to vertue, and the higher the vertue is, the more difficultie is in the atteynyng
<pb facs="tcp:4934:68"/> of hit: and the kyngedome of heuen muſte be gotte with a violence. It is eaſye to buylde churches and monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, to gyue bokes and chalices to the ſeruice of god, if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue wherwith: for laude and prayſe, and a worldly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentation foloweth commonly vpon it: but in doinge dedes of charitie to our neighbour, there be ſo manye difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that it maye anone diſcourage a man to contynewe in hit, but he doo it purely for god. Howe be hit I meane not that of gyuyng of almes to poore men that aſke it by waye of almeſſe in the ſtretes: but I meane hit of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytable dedes to be done to theym, that fyght with pouertye, and be aſhamed to aſke it: neuer the leſſe the diffycul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes therof I wylle not expreſſe at this tyme.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo it is a ryght great grace, that ſuche a deſyre is come amonge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to haue pore men releued. But ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly if it comme to this poynte hereafter, that ſpirituall menne wyll procure for
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:4934:68"/> theyr owne aduauntage, and lyttelle for poore menne: that deſyre for poore menne wylle ſoone ſlake and vanyſſhe aweye hereafter, as hit hath doone in tyme paſte.</p>
               <p>¶And as to the goynge on pylgre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, me thynketh it may be accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſet in the loweſt degre of good warkes: in ſo moche, that as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if a man in doinge ſuche pylgre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage ſpend large money for his coſtes and offerynge, that if he wolde diſpoſe moche leſſe thenne that, at hoome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge his poore neighbours: that he ſhoulde more highely pleaſe our lorde therby, or our ladye, or other ſayncte that he gothe to, and ſoner opteyne his iuſte petitions therby, than by all his great expences in his pylgremage and his labour bothe. And though he gyue almes to ſome poore men by the weye: yet is he more bounden to his poore neyghboures at whome, and moore thanke ſhall he haue of god, yf he loke charitably vnto them.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4934:69"/>
               <p>¶Alſo it is right expedient, that prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ofte inſtruct their audience, that the prayer of a good laye manne more pleſeth god, then the prayer of an yuel prieſte, or of an yuel religious manne. And to inſtructe them alſo, that vocall prayer is not the only thyng that pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, though it be ſingularly good in it ſelfe: for the true and iuſt labour of the peple is alſo a right good prayer. How be it if they ſomtyme vſe vocal prayer, when they maye come to it, they do the better. And therfore I thinke verilye, that if a good lay man pray, that ſuche an other man, or ſuche that percaſe be his benefactours, may be part takers of all his iuſte and true labour, that it ſhall profite the other man more, then the vocalle prayer of many other that be not good.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo it is expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that they induce the people, al that they can, to do their good dedes here, ere they departe out of this worlde. And diligentlye to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe theym, that if they can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tente
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:4934:69"/> for the loue of god and of their neyghbour, to departe frely with a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel portion of their goodes here in this lyfe, that they myght kepe ſtyll if they wolde: they ſhall haue more rewarde of god for it, then they ſhall haue for a right great ſubſtance of goodes giuen for theym after their deth, when they canne not occupye theym, though they wolde.</p>
               <p>¶Alſo that they ſtyrre the people, to leaue the curioſitie of burialles, that hath ben vſed in many places in tyme paſte: for they be rather comfortes to the frendes that be on lyue, then any profite to the ſoules of theym that be departed. And yf the charge of ſuche pompe were tourned into dooles, to be ſent to poore men home to theyr howſes, I thynke it wolde pleaſe our lorde ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye moche.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:4934:70"/>
            <head>¶Whether it be laufulle to warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſt Turkes and ſaraſyns. The fyfth Chapitre.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>YZAN.</speaker>
               <p>Syth thou haſte now at my deſyre ſpoken of thynges concernyng abuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that as the thynkethe, wold be reformed, I pray the ſpeke ſom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>what nowe of the ſecte of Macumite. For euer ſithe the makyng of our firſt dialoge, I coud neuer forget, how gret a multitude of ſoules dayly peryſſhe therby.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>SA.</speaker>
               <p>And I wold gladly ſpeake therof, if I thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we coude do any good in that behalfe. But ſurely tylle a peace be had amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge chriſten men, it bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not to ſpeke any more of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> matter. And ouer that I haue perceyued, that ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be of the opinion, that it is not laufull for chriſten men to warre vpon the turkes, and to go about by compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to bring them to the faith. For they ſay, as the truth is, that faith is fre and can not be compelled: and therfore they
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:4934:70"/> ſay, that Macumete him ſelfe, is diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by many writers, bycauſe that in the beginning of his ſect he vſed vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence: And ſo I am ſomwhat in dout in that matter in my conceit, and wote not whether it be good to ſpeke any fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther in the mattier or not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>BIS.</speaker>
               <p>As to the fyrſt poynt that thou doubteſt in, al truſte is to be put in god, and he ſhall well helpe vs to the pece that we deſire. And as to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other poynt that thou haſt moued, I lytel regard it. For I am wel aſſured, that if they them ſelf that be of that opinion, conſidered al the mattier as it is, that they wolde ſhortly change their myndes therin. For ſith the turkes haue many countreis, that chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue good right to: it is no doute, but that it is laufull for chriſten princis to warre vpon them, &amp; driue them out, as they myght do chriſten men, that were vſurpers. And alſo if infidelles inuade chriſten realmes, and by power wolde take them into their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, it is laufull for chriſten princis in the title of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4934:71"/> ſo were lykely to be wrongfully put out of their countrey to reſiſte them, and to kepe the Chriſtians in their right.</p>
               <p>And all the infidels that be ſo inuaded, to take them as their ennemies, and to punyſhe theym as ennemies, in ſuche maner as they ſhall thinke expedient, by dethe or otherwiſe. But then in theſe caſes, if the chriſtians preuayled, and than the infidels wolde be conuerted, and the chriſten men for fauour of the faith wold gyue them their lyues, were it nat good charite to do it? And if they wyl not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted: and then the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men put them to deth, for that they be enemies, is it not olſo laufull? And yet hit can not be ſaide there, that they be put to dethe, bycauſe they wyll not beleue, but bycauſe they be ennemies, as I haue ſaid before. And in this caſe ſtandeth the countreyes of Conſtanty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble, and of Ieruſalem. For they were longe in the handes of chriſten men, er that they came into the handes eyther of the turkes, or of the Saraſins. And
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:4934:71"/> as for Conſtantynoble it is but of late yeres, that the turkes with power and without title toke the emperour and all the empier into their handes, and with greatte crueltie ſawed the emperour a ſonder in the myddes with a ſawe of tree. And it is yet knowen amonge the chriſten men, that be there in captiuite, who is the very heire of blode vnto the the empire: why is it not then laufull to chriſten princis to reſtore hym ageyn to his inheritaunce, and to diſtroye all them that wyll reſyſt them? Neuer the les in ſome caſe a doubte myghte ryſe, whether chriſten men might inuade in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelles in a countrey, whiche they had wrongefully taken into their handes: as if infydels wrongefully inuade an other countrey, that were alſo infidels, and that was neuer chriſtened, and put the very owners out therof, whether it were lauful for chriſten princis to driue them out, and reſtore the fyrſte infidels into their right agayn or not. And this me thinketh, maye be right well ſaide
<pb facs="tcp:4934:72"/> therin: that yf the people that ſo hathe inuaded, be the more cruell people then the firſte were, wherby it is great peryl and danger vnto chriſten realmes, that lye nygh adioynynge vnto theym, that they wyll hereafter inuade them alſo, if they be ſuffered: that then it is laufull for chriſten princis to driue them out, in eſchewyng of that da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, &amp; to reſtore the firſt infidels agayne to their right. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if thoſe firſt infidels for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fauer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue found in chriſten men wyll be conuerted to the faith, I ſuppoſe no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wil ſay, but that it is wel done to ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cept them. But if they wold not in that caſe be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted of their fre wil, I wyll wel agre, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they muſt be ſuffrid to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſtil in their infidelitie, as they dyd before, tyl our lord ſhal of his goodnes cal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to grace. And thus me thinkith it is but a litel doubt, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is laufull for chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> princis to make war ageinſt all the infidels, that be inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cities of Conſtantinoble &amp; Ieruſalem, and al the countreis ther about, that al
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:4934:72"/> any tyme were in the handes of chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men, before they were in the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of the turkes, or of the Saraſins, and to put theym to dethe that wylle reſyſte them, as ennemies. And thus haue I nowe ſhewed the my conceyte concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge that doute, whether it be laufull for chriſten men to warre vpon infidels or not. How be it if they coude without battayle be conuerted by preachinge or epiſtles without ſheding of blode, that were ſurely the beſt way: But the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be now ſo far roted in malyce, that they haue made a lawe, that no man v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon peyne of deth ſhall preche ageinſte their lawes. Wherfore it ſemeth, that chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men may not now with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſende any preacher vnto them. And yf any precher of zele of martyrdom wold of his free wyl deſyre to goo thyther: yet it were to me a great dout, whether hit were better for chryſten men to ſtop hym, if they coulde, ſo that he myghte do more good another way at hoome: and not to ſuffre hym wylfully to renne
<pb facs="tcp:4934:73"/> vnto his deth or not: Specially when there is no lykelyhode, that any good ſhall folowe vpon his goinge. For the preachynge to the turkes nowe in theſe dayes, is nothynge lyke to the preching to the gentyls in the begynnyng of the faithe. For then the gentyls wolde ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes here it. And thervpon many tourned to the faith: and though ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme preachers were therfore putte to dethe, not withſtandynge I agre well, that it was good charitie for other pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to ieoparde to doo the ſame. For many tymes great increaſe of the faith folowed therby. But as to the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes nowe in theſe dayes, their malice is ſo greatte, that there is no likelihod that our prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſhuld be hard amonge them, as I haue ſayde before.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:4934:73"/>
            <list>
               <head>¶The Table.</head>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He introduction. fo. i.</item>
               <item>Of dyuers abuſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge the ſeuen ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and dyuers other thinges. The firſt chaptre. <abbr>Memorand</abbr> that in the ſayd fyrſt Cha. be conteyned .xxx. paragraffes, wherof the fyrſte treateth of the ſacrament of anoylynge. folio. 2.</item>
               <item>The ſeconde paragraffe treteth of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienge of paryſheners by theyr cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes folio. eodem.</item>
               <item>The .iii. paragrafe treateth of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of confirmation. fo. eodem.</item>
               <item>The .iiii. paragraff treateth of the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hibiting of biſhops to gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ꝑdon. fo. 3.</item>
               <item>The .v. paragraffe treateth of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing confeſſion from curates to the byſhops fo. eodem.</item>
               <item>The .vi. paragraffe treteth of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitynge of the people from howſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge. folio. 4.</item>
               <item>The .vii. paragrafe treateth of curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:4934:74"/> buyldynges of ſpirituall menne: And of the apparelle therof. fo. eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</item>
               <item>The .viii. paragrafe treateth of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plens and ſeruyng prieſtes. fo. eodem.</item>
               <item>The .ix. paragrafe treteth that the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of irregularite be ouer ſtrayt. f. 5.</item>
               <item>The .x. paragrafe treteth, that the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of relygions be very ſtrayte to be kepte in theſe dayes. fo eodem.</item>
               <item>The .xi. paragrafe treteth howe cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes clayme as hyghe power in their poſſeſſions &amp; goodes as lay men. fo. 6.</item>
               <item>The .xii. paragraffe treateth of the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of prieſtes. fo. eodem.</item>
               <item>The .xiii. paragrafe treateth of viſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. folio. 7.</item>
               <item>The .xiiii. paragrafe treateth of a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie newly ryſen ageinſt the ſtatute of pluralites, and none reſidence. fo. 8.</item>
               <item>The .xv. paragrafe treateth of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to oure neyghbour, and other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde dedes. fo. eod.</item>
               <item>The .xvi. paragrafe treateth that ſom prechers haue preached for their own profyt &amp; ſingularite in time paſt. fo. 11.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:4934:74"/>
               <item>The .xvii. paragrafe treateth, howe prieſtes accompte a defaulte in oone prieſte to ſounde to the defaulte of an other. folio. 12.</item>
               <item>The .xviii. paragrafe treateth, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the .x. part of tithes be due by the lawe of god. fo. 14.</item>
               <item>The .xix. paragrafe treateth, howe in ſom caſes they ought in ſpiritual cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes to iudge after the lawe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme. folio eodem.</item>
               <item>The .xx. paragrafe treateth, that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall men nowe accept thynges, that ſpirituall menne refuſed in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the churche. fo. 15.</item>
               <item>The .xxi. paragrafe treteth, that ſome religious men prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their profeſſion to be the ſureſt way to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. fo. eo.</item>
               <item>The .xxii. paragrafe tretith, how ſom ouer lyghtly report, that there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heritikes. fo. eodem.</item>
               <item>The .xxiii. paragrafe treateth of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes and paſtures beynge in the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of ſpirituall men. fo. 16.</item>
               <item>The .xxiiii. paragrafe treateth, howe
<pb facs="tcp:4934:75"/> ſpiritual men, as it is reported, be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrayte in makynge of leaſes, rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge of rentes, and makynge of fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. &amp;c. folio. 17.</item>
               <item>The .xxv. parag. treteth, how their de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formities of body that ſhuld be priſtis hath ben myslyked in tyme paſt. fo. 18.</item>
               <item>The .xxvi. paragraffe treateth of dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers cerimonies in the church. fo. eod.</item>
               <item>The .xxvii. paragrafe treateth of byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and kynges canoniſed fo. 19.</item>
               <item>The .xviii. paragrafe treateth of the auctoritie of canoniſation. fo. 20.</item>
               <item>The .xxix. paragraffe treateth of this decree <hi>Omnis uttiuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſexus.</hi> fo. 28.</item>
               <item>The .xxx. paragrafe treateth of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that many of the clergie haue preched for their own profite, and that yet they do nothynge to remoue them out of that opinion. fo. 33.</item>
               <item>¶Who is the hygher iudge in ſuche corrections as be called ſpirituall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, the kynge or the clergie. The ſeconde chapitre. fo. 34.</item>
               <item>¶Of dyuerſe thynges concernynge
<pb facs="tcp:4934:75"/> ſaynte Thomas of Canturburye. The iii. Chapitre. fo. 53.</item>
               <item>¶Of certayne thinges, that ſhoulde ſeme to be occaſions to brynge good peace and quyetnes betwyxte the cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gye and the people. The fourthe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitre. folio. 61.</item>
               <item>¶Whether it be lawfulle to warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſte the Turkes and Saraſyns. The fyfthe Chapitre. fo. 69.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS TABVLAE.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>¶Fautes in printynge.</head>
            <p>FOlio. 5. pagi. 2. li. 17. rede after diſpenſations be. Folio. 12. pagi. 2. fin. 13. rede that it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of. Fo. 14. pa. 1. linea. 14. rede, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions. Fo. 18. pag. 1. linea. 9. rede after ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, than to be extreme. Fo. 26. pag. 1. li. 14. rede ſemeth. <hi>Fo.</hi> 31. pag. 1. li. 5. rede article. Fo. 36. pa. 1. lin. 1. rede ſuche after haue. Fo. 40. pa. 2. li. 23. for execution rede excommunication. Fo. 42. pag. 1. li. 9. for noteth, rede writeth. Fo. 46. pa. 1. lin. 6. et. 7. for excommunications, rede examinations. Fo. 48. pa. 1. li. 20. rede there is. Fo. 50. pa. 1. li. 3. after <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittenda,</hi> rede is this. Folio. 51. pag. 1. lin. 7. rede, crueltie. Fo. 59. pa. 2. lin. 10. for hight, rede high. Fo. 64. pa. 1. li. 1. rede deceyued.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
